<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="file:/V:/AcctsG/10878/CSS/10878.css" alternate="no"?><?conv mccps;head?><?conv setverso;GWINNETT COUNTY CODE?><?conv setrecto;PLANNING AND DEVELOPMENT?><?conv setguide;single?><?conv setllpg;1;0;0;3?><?conv setrev;Supp. No. 16?><?conv setgtext;?><section xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         id="x85D3CE73D5FA"
         class="chapter"
         data-type="chapter"
         data-pubmap="level2"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml file:/V:/FuturePub/SCHEMA/HTMLBookMCC/htmlbookMCC.xsd">
   <header>
	     <h1 id="x85D3CE73D61B">Chapter 86</h1>
	     <p data-type="subtitle">Planning and Development<a class="footnoteref" href="#CH086_1" id="RCH086_1">*</a>
      </p>
   </header>

   <aside class="footnote" id="CH086_1">
	     <p class="footnotemark">
         <a href="#RCH086_1">[*]</a>
      </p>

      <p class="refcross1">Buildings and building regulations, ch. 14; businesses, ch. 18; environment, ch. 42; floods, ch. 50; historical preservation, ch. 58; manufactured homes and trailers, ch. 70; subdivisions, ch. 102; telecommunications, ch. 108; utilities, ch. 114; zoning resolution, app. D.</p>

      <p class="refstatelaw1">Authority to adopt plans and exercise the power of zoning, Ga. Const. art. 9, sec. 2, par. 4; Development Authorities Law, O.C.G.A. § 36-62-1 et seq.; The Zoning Procedures Law, O.C.G.A. § 36-66-1 et seq.; local government zoning powers, O.C.G.A. § 36-66-2; conflicts of interest in zoning actions, O.C.G.A. § 36-67A-1 et seq.; coordinated and comprehensive planning by counties and municipalities, O.C.G.A. § 36-70-1 et seq.; effect of zoning laws on covenants running with the land, O.C.G.A. § 44-5-60; regional development centers, O.C.G.A. § 50-8-30 et seq.</p>

   </aside>

<?xpp minitoc?>

<section id="x85D3CE73D65D"
            class="article"
            data-type="sect1"
            data-pubmap="level3">
      <header>
	        <h1 id="x85D3CE73D66B">Article I.</h1>
	        <p id="x85D3CE73D676" data-type="subtitle">In General</p>
      </header>

      <section id="x85D3CE73D690"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73D69F">Sec. 86-1.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73D6AA" data-type="subtitle">Incorporation by Reference.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D6C2" class="p1">The Development Regulations of Gwinnett County adopted January 5, 1988, and reprinted June, 1991, together with all amendments are incorporated by reference as part of this Code. An official copy of such ordinance and amendments is on file in the office of the clerk of the board of commissioners.</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73D6DD"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73D6EB">Sec. 86-2.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73D6F5" data-type="subtitle">Enforcement and Organization Generally.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D70E" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">The planning division shall prepare and update as necessary future plans for the unincorporated portions of the county regarding land use types and locations, transportation facilities and other county resources and facilities, and shall review all proposed amendments to the county zoning resolution and prepare recommendations thereon for the board of commissioners.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D727" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">The development division, unless otherwise specifically provided in this Code, shall enforce the following provisions of this Code, including inspection and permit issuance under the subdivision and zoning regulations and each building, plumbing or other technical code adopted in this chapter:</span>
         </p>

         <table id="x85D3CE73D749" class="std-2">
            <caption/>
            <colgroup data-cols="3">
	              <col width="3.23%"/>
	              <col width="64.52%"/>
	              <col width="32.25%"/>
            </colgroup>

            <thead/>

            <tbody>

               <tr>
	                 <td>(1)</td>
	                 <td>Construction codes .....</td>
	                 <td>§ 14-26 et seq.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>(2)</td>
	                 <td>Erosion and sedimentation control .....</td>
	                 <td>§ 42-96 et seq.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>(3)</td>
	                 <td>Moving and demolition of buildings  .....</td>
	                 <td>§ 14-86 et seq.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>(4)</td>
	                 <td>Erection permits for tall structures  .....</td>
	                 <td>§ 14-116 et seq.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>(5)</td>
	                 <td>Floodplain management  .....</td>
	                 <td>Ch. 50</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>(6)</td>
	                 <td>Subdivision regulations  .....</td>
	                 <td>Ch. 102</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>(7)</td>
	                 <td>Zoning regulation  .....</td>
	                 <td>App. D</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>(8)</td>
	                 <td>Occupancy limits for residential property  .....</td>
	                 <td>§ 14-146 et seq.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>(9)</td>
	                 <td>Buffer, landscape and tree ordinance  .....</td>
	                 <td>§ 118-1</td>
               </tr>
            </tbody>
         </table>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D857" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">The director of the development division or a designee thereof shall be the enforcement official for each technical code adopted in this chapter, and the qualifications and organization of inspectors or other enforcement personnel shall be established under rules and regulations of the department or county notwithstanding the requirements of any technical code adopted in this chapter.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D874" class="historynote1">(Code 1978, § 6-1001)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73D88F"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73D89D">Sec. 86-3.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73D8A8" data-type="subtitle">Departmental Duties of Planning and Development Divisions.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D8BF" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">The planning division and its director of the division shall perform the following duties:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D8D7" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Maintain correct land use maps and files of all zoning amendments.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D8EF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Prepare and recommend land use, transportation and other resource and facility plans to the board of commissioners.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D907" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Prepare recommendations on all zoning amendments for consideration by the board of commissioners, and generally provide for the application, noticing and hearing requirements of the amendment process.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D91F" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Prepare and maintain data, maps or other information regarding population, employment and economic characteristics of the county and land development activities, including subdivisions and building permits.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D937" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Conduct the review and certification process required by the state metropolitan river protection act, as amended.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B95BB" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">The director of the planning division shall serve as secretary to the planning and zoning commission, shall take and prepare its minutes and shall forward the minutes to the board of commissioners.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D966" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">The development division and its director shall perform the following duties:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D97D" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Provide for the orderly and safe development of the county through the provisions of the county subdivision regulations and other application regulations or standards as may be adopted by the board of commissioners.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73D995" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Prepare recommendations on all requests for variances from the provisions of the county zoning resolution, and generally provide for the application, noticing and hearing requirements of the zoning variances process.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x156991AC22E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Enforce the development regulations and standards of the zoning resolution.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DA15" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Enforce the county sediment control ordinance. This is a joint function with the engineering department.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DA5B" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Enforce the county building, electrical, plumbing, and heating and air conditioning codes.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B95DF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Enforce development compliance with the state metropolitan river protection act, as amended.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DADC" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">The director of development shall serve as secretary to the board of zoning appeals, shall take and prepare its minutes, and shall forward the minutes to the board of commissioners.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DAFF" class="historynote1">(Code 1978, § 6-1002)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="xD61FB0B95E9"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73DB29">Sec. 86-4.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73DB34" data-type="subtitle">Withdrawal of Zoning Amendment Applications.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="xD61FB0B95EE" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">It is the policy of the board of commissioners that an applicant for an amendment to the zoning map may withdraw such application without prejudice only until such time as the legal advertisement of a public hearing thereon is placed.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DB64" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">No application shall be allowed to be withdrawn under any circumstances after public notice of the public hearings has been placed. All applications having been advertised shall be considered by the board of commissioners and shall receive final action.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DB7D" class="historynote1">(Code 1978, § 6-1003)</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DB8D" class="refcross1">Zoning, app. D.</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73DBA4"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73DBB2">Secs. 86-5—86-30.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73DBBC" data-type="subtitle" data-widowtype="no">Reserved.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DBD6" class="left"/>

      </section>

   </section>

   <section id="xD61FB0B95FF"
            class="article"
            data-type="sect1"
            data-pubmap="level3">
      <header>
	        <h1 id="x85D3CE73DC04">Article II.</h1>
	        <p data-type="subtitle">Municipal-Gwinnett County Planning Commission<a class="footnoteref" href="#CH086_2" id="RCH086_2">†</a>
         </p>
      </header>

      <aside class="footnote" id="CH086_2">
	        <p class="footnotemark">
            <a href="#RCH086_2">[†]</a>
         </p>

         <p class="refcross1">Authorities, boards, commissions and committees, § 2-166 et seq.</p>

      </aside>

      <section id="x85D3CE73DC34"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73DC42">Sec. 86-31.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73DC4C" data-type="subtitle">Municipal-County Planning Commission.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DC63" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Participating jurisdictions.</i> Any municipality in the county that wishes to participate in the municipal-county planning commission may do so by enacting an appropriate ordinance. Thereafter, a member appointed by the municipality may participate in all discussion before the commission, and may vote on any issue which affects property within the city limits.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DC7D" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Planning commission membership.</i>
            </span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DC94" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">The municipal-county planning commission shall consist of nine members who are residents of the county and residents of the district from which they are appointed and who shall be appointed by the county commissioners as outlined in this subsection, and one member who is a resident of each of the participating municipalities and who shall be appointed by the governing authority of the municipality as outlined in this subsection.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DCAD" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Each incumbent district commissioner shall appoint two members who shall reside in their respective districts, and the commission chairman shall appoint one member who resides in any district of the county to the planning commission. These members of the planning commission shall serve at the pleasure of the county board of commissioners. Any action to remove a member of the planning commission shall only be initiated by the appointing county commissioner.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DCC7" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Organization, rules, staff and finances.</i>
            </span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DCDE" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">The planning commission shall elect its chairman and vice-chairman from among its members. The chairman and vice-chairman shall serve for one year or until reelected or until a successor is elected. The planning commission shall appoint a secretary, who may be an officer or employee of the county or of one of the participating municipalities.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DCF7" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">The planning commission shall adopt its own rules of procedure. It shall meet at least once each month at the call of the chairman and at such other times as the chairman or the members shall determine. All meetings of the planning commission at which official action is taken shall be open to the public. The planning commission shall keep a record of its resolutions, transactions, findings and determinations; and all of its records shall be public records.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DD10" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">The planning commission may appoint such employees and staff as it may deem necessary for its work and may contract with or accept funds from federal, state or local public or semipublic agencies or private individuals or corporations. It may contract with city planners and other consultants for such services as it may require. Its expenditures, exclusive of gifts, shall be within the amounts appropriated for the purpose by the governing authorities of the county and participating municipalities.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DD2A" class="historynote1">(Code 1978, § 1-5028; Ord. of 1-5-93(3); Ord. of 7-15-03)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73DD44"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73DD52">Secs. 86-32—86-50.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73DD5C" data-type="subtitle" data-widowtype="no">Reserved.</p>
         </header>

      </section>

   </section>

   <section id="x85D3CE73DD83"
            class="article"
            data-type="sect1"
            data-pubmap="level3">
      <header>
	        <h1 id="x85D3CE73DD91">Article III.</h1>
	        <p data-type="subtitle">Development Advisory Committee<a class="footnoteref" href="#CH086_3" id="RCH086_3">‡</a>
         </p>
      </header>

      <aside class="footnote" id="CH086_3">
	        <p class="footnotemark">
            <a href="#RCH086_3">[‡]</a>
         </p>

         <p class="refcross1">Authorities, boards, commissions and committees, § 2-166 et seq.</p>

      </aside>

      <section id="x85D3CE73DDBF"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73DDCD">Sec. 86-51.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73DDD7" data-type="subtitle">Creation.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DDEF" class="p1">There is hereby created a county development advisory committee to serve at the pleasure of the board of commissioners and for such duration as the board may desire.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DE3D" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 10-15-91(a); Res. of 9-7-93(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="xD61FB0B963C"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73DE66">Sec. 86-52.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73DE70" data-type="subtitle">Purposes.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DE87" class="p1">The purposes of the development advisory committee shall be to:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DE97" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Advise the board of commissioners and the department of planning and development, referred to as the department in this article, on issues and matters of concern with regard to land development activities and regulations.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DEAF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Assist the department in the interpretation and implementation of land development regulations.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DEC7" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Review proposed new land development regulations and amendments and advise the department and the board of commissioners on their impact and effectiveness.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DEE1" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Carry out such studies or investigations regarding the land development regulatory process or requirements as the board of commissioners may request from time to time.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DEFF" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 10-15-91(b); Res. of 9-7-93(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73DF44"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="xD61FB0B9655">Sec. 86-53.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73DF5D" data-type="subtitle">Appointment.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DF74" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Membership.</i> The development advisory committee shall consist of 20 members, with at least one member each representing or having the following qualifications:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DF8C" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">One citizen representative per commissioner, five members total.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DFA3" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Planning commission member.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DFBA" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Zoning board of appeals member.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DFD1" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Residential subdivider.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9664" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Office developer, industrial developer, and commercial developer.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73DFFF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Multifamily developer.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E016" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">Homebuilder.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E02C" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">Registered professional engineer.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E043" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(9)</span>
            <span class="li">Registered land surveyor.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E05B" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(10)</span>
            <span class="li">Registered landscape architect.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E072" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(11)</span>
            <span class="li">Utilities coordinating committee member.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E089" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(12)</span>
            <span class="li">Municipal member of the county comprehensive plan coordinating committee.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E0A0" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Term of office.</i> Members shall be appointed to serve two calendar-year terms. Appointments shall be effective January 1 of the first year of term, and members shall serve until replaced. In order to establish permanent staggered terms, initial appointment terms will be as follows:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9679" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Two years (group one membership).</i>
            </span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E0D1" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">a.</span>
            <span class="li">Three citizen representatives, districts 2 and 4, and at-large.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E0E8" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">b.</span>
            <span class="li">Planning commission member.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E103" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">c.</span>
            <span class="li">Registered professional engineer.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E11A" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">d.</span>
            <span class="li">Registered architect.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E131" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">e.</span>
            <span class="li">Homebuilder.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E148" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">f.</span>
            <span class="li">Multifamily developer.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E15F" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">g.</span>
            <span class="li">Office developer.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E176" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">h.</span>
            <span class="li">Utilities coordinating committee member.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E18E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>One year (group two membership).</i>
            </span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E1A5" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">a.</span>
            <span class="li">Two citizen representatives, districts 1 and 3.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E1BC" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">b.</span>
            <span class="li">Zoning board of appeals member.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E1D3" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">c.</span>
            <span class="li">Registered land surveyor.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E1E9" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">d.</span>
            <span class="li">Registered landscape architect.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E200" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">e.</span>
            <span class="li">General contractor.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E217" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">f.</span>
            <span class="li">Single-family developer.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E22E" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">g.</span>
            <span class="li">Commercial developer.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E245" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">h.</span>
            <span class="li">Industrial developer.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E25B" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">i.</span>
            <span class="li">Municipal member of the county comprehensive plan coordinating committee.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E276" class="left">Following the development advisory committee's first year, all terms will be for two years.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B96A7" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Nominations.</i> For appointments to the development advisory committee, the board of commissioners shall seek and consider nominations from the following organizations at a minimum, if in existence:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E29E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">County developer's association.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B96AC" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Council for quality growth.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E2CF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Apartment owners and managers association.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E2E6" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Gwinnett Chapter, Home Builders Association of Metropolitan Atlanta.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E2FD" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Planning commission.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E314" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Zoning board of appeals.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E32B" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">County utilities coordinating committee.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E342" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">County comprehensive plan coordinating committee.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E398" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(d)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Replacements.</i> A member appointed to fill a vacancy which occurs during a year shall be appointed to fill the unexpired term of the vacant position for the remainder of the calendar year.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E3B1" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(e)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Compensation.</i> The members of the development advisory committee shall serve without compensation or reimbursement of any kind. Normal costs of operations, such as meeting space, minutes, etc., shall be borne by the county through the department.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E3CA" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(f)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Limitation.</i> No employee of the county government may be a member of the development advisory committee.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E3E1" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 10-15-91(c); Res. of 9-7-93(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73E3FB"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73E414">Sec. 86-54.</h2>
	           <p id="x156991AC248" data-type="subtitle">Officers.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E437" class="p1">The members of the development advisory committee shall elect from among their number a chairman, vice-chairman, and such other officers as the committee may desire, for terms determined by the committee.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B96D4" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 10-15-91(d); Res. of 9-7-93(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73E462"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="xD61FB0B96D8">Sec. 86-55.</h2>
	           <p id="xD61FB0B96D9" data-type="subtitle">Meetings.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E491" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">The development advisory committee shall meet at the call of its chairman, at such times as the committee may deem appropriate, or upon the call of the board of commissioners or the director of the department. Under no circumstances shall the committee meetings be called less often than once every two calendar months.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E4AA" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">The development advisory committee may choose to adopt such bylaws for the conduct of its meetings as it deems necessary or appropriate.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E4C2" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">Basic administrative support for the committee shall be coordinated or provided by the staff of the department.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B96E3" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(d)</span>
            <span class="li">The director of the department shall provide for the keeping of a record of the development advisory committee's actions and recommendations. The director shall be responsible for the transmittal of the record and of all communications and recommendations directed from the committee to the board of commissioners, in their normal course of business.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E4F8" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(e)</span>
            <span class="li">Meetings of the development advisory committee shall be open to all parties. While the committee may invite any person to participate or involve any person in its discussions and deliberations, all matters requiring formal decisions shall be decided only by a vote of the appointed members.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E511" class="historynote1">(Code 1978, § 1-5029; Ord. of 10-15-91; Res. of 9-7-93(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73E52B"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73E539">Secs. 86-56—86-69.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73E543" data-type="subtitle" data-widowtype="no">Reserved.</p>
         </header>

      </section>

   </section>

   <section id="xD61FB0B96F1"
            class="article"
            data-type="sect1"
            data-pubmap="level3">
      <header>
	        <h1 id="x85D3CE73E577">Article IV.</h1>
	        <p data-type="subtitle">Adult Entertainment Establishments<a class="footnoteref" href="#CH086_4" id="RCH086_4">**</a>
         </p>
      </header>

      <aside class="footnote" id="CH086_4">
	        <p class="footnotemark">
            <a href="#RCH086_4">[**]</a>
         </p>

         <p class="refcross1">Adult entertainment establishments, § 18-291 et seq; video stores, § 18-352.</p>

      </aside>

      <section id="x85D3CE73E5A8"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73E5B6">Sec. 86-70.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73E5C0" data-type="subtitle">Findings; Public Purpose.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E5DB" class="p1">Based on the experiences of other counties and municipalities, including, but not limited to, Austin, Texas and Garden Grove, California, which experiences are found to be relevant to the problems faced by Gwinnett County, Georgia; and based on the documentary evidence and oral testimony presented by a law enforcement professional and an expert in economic development, both of whom are familiar with conditions resulting in other localities, at the board of commissioners' hearing on July 17, 2001; and based on the evidence and testimony of persons who have appeared before members of the county board of commissioners on other occasions including the public hearing conducted on May 26, 1998 and on documentary evidence submitted to the board of commissioners, the county board of commissioners takes note of the well-known and self-evident conditions and secondary effects attendant to the commercial exploitation of human sexuality, which do not vary greatly among the various communities within our country.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E5F0" class="p1">It is the finding of the board of commissioners of the county that public nudity (either partial or total) under certain circumstances, particularly circumstances related to the sale and consumption of alcoholic beverages in establishments offering live nude entertainment or "adult entertainment," (whether such alcoholic beverages are sold on the premises or not) begets criminal behavior and tends to create undesirable community conditions. In the same manner, establishments offering cinematographic or videographic adult entertainment have the same deleterious effects on the community.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E606" class="p1">Among the acts of criminal behavior found to be associated with the commercial combination of live nudity and alcohol, live commercial nudity in general, and cinematographic or videographic adult entertainment are disorderly conduct, prostitution, public solicitation, public indecency, drug use and drug trafficking. Among the undesirable community conditions identified in other communities with the commercial combination of live nudity and alcohol, commercial nudity in general, and cinematographic or videographic adult entertainment are depression of property values and acceleration of community blight in the surrounding neighborhood, increased allocation of and expenditure for law enforcement personnel to preserve law and order, and increased burden on the judicial system as a consequence of the criminal behavior hereinabove described. The board of commissioners finds it is reasonable to believe that some or all of these undesirable community conditions will result in the county, as well.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E61A" class="p1">Furthermore, it is the finding of the county board of commissioners that other forms of adult entertainment including, but not limited to, adult book stores, adult novelty shops, adult video stores, peep shows, adult theaters, and massage parlors have an adverse effect upon the quality of life in surrounding communities.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E62D" class="p1">The board of commissioners finds that the negative secondary effects of adult entertainment establishments upon the county are similar whether the adult entertainment establishment features live nude dancing or sells video tapes depicting sexual activities. In addition, the county's experience with the adult bookstore located within the county on Jimmy Carter Boulevard has shown that a substantial amount of activity at the bookstore involves booths which an individual may enter, view videos depicting sexual activity, and sexually interact with a bookstore patron in an adjoining booth through a hole strategically placed in the wall of adjoining booths.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E671" class="p1">The board of commissioners of the county therefore finds that it is in the best interests of the health, welfare, safety and morals of the community and the preservation of its businesses, neighborhoods, and of churches, schools, residential areas, public parks and children's day care facilities to prevent or reduce the adverse impacts of adult entertainment establishments. Therefore, the board of commissioners of the county finds that licensing and regulations are necessary for any adult entertainment establishment. The board finds that these regulations promote the public welfare by furthering legitimate public and governmental interests, including but not limited to, reducing criminal activity and protecting against or eliminating undesirable community conditions and further finds that such will not infringe upon the protected Constitutional rights of freedom of speech or expression. To that end, this article is hereby adopted.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E686" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2); Ord. of 4-25-02(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73E6A3"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73E6B1">Sec. 86-71.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73E6BC" data-type="subtitle">Definitions.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E6D6" class="p1">Except as specifically defined herein, all words used in this article shall be as defined in the most recent edition of the New Illustrated Book of Development Definitions (Rutgers). Words not defined herein or in the above book shall be construed to have the meaning given by common and ordinary use, and shall be interpreted within the context of the sentence and section in which they occur.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E6EB" class="p1">
            <i>Adult bookstore</i> means any commercial establishment in which more than ten square feet of floor space is used for the display or offer for sale of any book or publication, film, or other medium which depicts sexually explicit nudity or sexual conduct by its emphasis on matter depicting, describing or relating to specified sexual activities or specified anatomical areas.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E6FF" class="p1">
            <i>Adult entertainer</i> means any person employed by an adult entertainment establishment who exposes his or her "specified anatomical areas," as defined herein. For purposes of this section, adult entertainers include employees as well as independent contractors.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E717" class="p1">
            <i>Adult entertainment</i> means entertainment that is characterized by an emphasis on the depiction, display or the featuring of "specified anatomical areas."</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E728" class="p1">
            <i>Adult entertainment establishment</i> shall be defined to include the following types of business:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E739" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Any commercial establishment that employs or uses any person live, in any capacity in the sale or service of beverages or food while such person is unclothed or in such attire, costume or clothing, so as to expose any portion of his or her "specified anatomical areas," as defined herein;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E755" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Any commercial establishment which provides live entertainment where any person appears unclothed or in such attire, costume or clothing as to expose any portion of his or her "specified anatomical areas" as defined herein or where such performances are distinguished or characterized by an emphasis on "specified sexual activities," as defined herein;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E76E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Any commercial establishment which holds, promotes, sponsors or allows any contest, promotion, special night, event or any other activity where live patrons of the establishment are encouraged or allowed to engage in any of the conduct described in subsections (1) and (2) herein;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E787" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Any commercial establishment having a substantial or significant portion of its stock in trade, books, magazines or other periodicals, videotapes or movies or other reproductions, whether for sale or rent, which are distinguished or characterized by their emphasis on matter depicting, describing or relating to "specified sexual activities" as defined herein or "specified anatomical areas" as defined herein or having a segment or section comprising more than ten square feet of its total floor space, devoted to the sale or display of such material or which derives more than five percent of its net sales from the sale or rental of such material;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E7A1" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Any commercial establishment utilizing an enclosed building with a capacity of 50 or more persons used for cinematographic or videographic presentation of material distinguished by or characterized by an emphasis on matter depicting, describing, or relating to "specified sexual activities" or "specified anatomical areas", as defined herein, for observation by patrons therein;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E7B9" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Any adult motion picture theater, adult motion picture arcade, adult mini-motion picture theater, adult bookstore, adult video store, adult hotel, or adult motel, as defined herein;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E7D2" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">The definition of "adult entertainment establishment" shall not include traditional or mainstream theater, which means a theater, movie theater, concert hall, museum, educational institution, or similar establishment which regularly features live or other performances or showings which are not distinguished or characterized by an emphasis on the depiction, display, or description or the featuring of specified anatomical areas or specified sexual activities in that the depiction, display, description or featuring is incidental to the primary purpose of any performance. Performances and showings are regularly featured when they comprise at least 80 percent of all annual performances or showings.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E7ED" class="p1">
            <i>Adult hotel or motel</i> means a hotel or motel wherein material is presented which is distinguished or characterized by an emphasis on matter depicting, describing or relating to specified sexual activities or specified anatomical areas.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E7FF" class="p1">
            <i>Adult mini-motion picture theater</i> means an enclosed building with a capacity for less than 50 persons used for presenting material distinguished or characterized by an emphasis on matter depicting or relating to specified sexual activities or specified anatomical areas for observation by patrons therein.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9735" class="p1">
            <i>Adult motion picture arcade</i> means any place to which the public is permitted to be invited wherein paper currency, coin- or slug-operated or electronically, electrically or mechanically controlled still or motion picture machines, projectors or other image-producing devices are maintained to show images to five or fewer persons per machine at any one time and where the images so displayed are distinguished or characterized by an emphasis on depicting or describing specified sexual activities or specified anatomical areas.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E824" class="p1">
            <i>Adult motion picture theater</i> means an enclosed building with a capacity of 50 or more persons, used for presenting material distinguished or characterized by an emphasis on matter depicting, describing or relating to specified sexual activities or specified anatomical areas for observation by patrons therein.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E86B" class="p1">
            <i>Adult video store</i> means any establishment having a substantial or significant portion of its stock in trade, video tapes or movies or other reproductions, whether for sale or rent, which are distinguished or characterized by an emphasis on matter depicting, describing or relating to specified sexual activities or specified anatomical areas, or an establishment with a segment or section, comprising five percent of its total floor space, devoted to the sale or display of such material or which derives more than five percent of its net sales from videos which are characterized or distinguished or relating to specified sexual activities or specified anatomical areas.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E87E" class="p1">
            <i>Operator</i> means the manager or other person principally in charge of an adult entertainment establishment.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E88F" class="p1">
            <i>Owner</i> means any individual or entity holding more than a 20 percent interest in an adult entertainment establishment.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E8A0" class="p1">
            <i>Premises</i> means the defined, closed or partitioned establishment, whether room, shop or building wherein adult entertainment is performed.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E8B1" class="p1">
            <i>Specified sexual activities</i> shall be defined to mean and include any of the following:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E8C2" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Actual or simulated sexual intercourse, oral copulation, anal intercourse, oral anal copulation, bestiality, direct physical stimulation of unclothed genitals, flagellation or torture in the context of a sexual relationship, or the use of excretory functions in the context of a sexual relationship and any of the following sexually oriented acts or conduct: anilingus, buggery, coprophagy, coprophilia, cunnilingus, fellatio, necrophilia, pederasty, pedophilia, piquerism, sapphism, zooerasty;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E8DB" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Use of human or animal ejaculation, sodomy, oral copulation, coitus or masturbation;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E8F3" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Fondling or other erotic touching of nude human genitals, pubic region, buttocks or female breast;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E90A" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Masochism, erotic or sexually oriented torture, beating or the infliction of pain; or</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E921" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Erotic or lewd touching, fondling or other sexual contact with an animal by a human being.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E939" class="p1">
            <i>Specified anatomical areas</i> shall include the following:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E949" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Less than completely and opaquely covered human genitals or pubic region, cleft of the buttocks, or female breast below a point immediately above the top of the areola; or</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E962" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Human male genitalia in a discernibly turgid state, even if completely and opaquely covered.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E97E" class="p1">
            <i>Children's day care facility</i> shall be defined as a structure or portion of a structure wherein is provided care and supervision of children away from their place of residence for less than 24 hours per day on a regular basis for compensation. For the purpose of this article the term "children's day care facility" shall include but not be limited to the terms "nursery school," "early learning center," "pre-kindergarten," "private kindergarten," "play school," or "pre-school."</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E991" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2); Amd. of 10-21-03(5), § 3)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73E9AA"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73E9B8">Sec. 86-72.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73E9C2" data-type="subtitle">License Required.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E9E2" class="p1">It shall be unlawful for any person, association, partnership, or corporation to operate, engage in, conduct, or carry on, in or upon any premises within the unincorporated area of the county an adult entertainment establishment as defined in this article without first procuring an annual license to do so except as provided in section 86-80(b) when the licensing and revenue manager fails to approve or deny an application for an adult entertainment license within 30 days as required by this article. The issuance of such an annual license shall not be deemed to authorize, condone or make legal any activity thereunder if the same is deemed illegal or unlawful under the laws of the state or the United States. No annual license for an adult entertainment establishment shall be issued by the county if the premises to be used also holds a license to sell alcoholic beverages or malt beverages and wine for consumption on the premises. Any premises licensed as an adult entertainment establishment shall not be eligible to apply at any time for a license to sell alcoholic beverages or malt beverages and wine for consumption on the premises. There shall be an annual regulatory fee for each adult entertainment establishment licensed within the county in the amount of $750.00. The annual regulatory fee must be paid to the licensing and revenue manager of the county within ten days after the licensing and revenue manager approves the initial application for an adult entertainment establishment license or a renewal thereof. In any event, no adult entertainment establishment license or renewal thereof shall be issued until the most recent annual regulatory fee has been paid. All licenses granted hereunder shall expire on December 31 of each year. Licensees who desire to renew their license shall file an application with the licensing and revenue manager on the form provided for renewal of the license for the ensuing year. Applications for renewal must be filed before November 30 of each year. Any renewal application received after November 30 shall pay, in addition to said annual regulatory fee, a late charge of 20 percent. If a license renewal application is received after January 1, such application shall be treated as an initial application and the applicant shall be required to comply with all rules and regulations for the granting of licenses as if no previous license had been held. If a license application is received after January 1, investigative and administrative costs as hereinafter set forth in this article will be assessed. All licenses granted hereunder shall be for the calendar year and the full annual regulatory fee must be paid for a license renewal application filed prior to July 1 of the license year. One-half of a full annual regulatory fee shall be paid for a license renewal application filed after July 1 of the license year. Any person renewing any license issued hereunder who shall pay the annual regulatory fee, or any portion thereof, after January 1, shall, in addition to said annual regulatory fee and late charges, pay simple interest on the delinquent balance at the annual rate then charged by the Internal Revenue Service of the United States on unpaid federal income taxes.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73E9FB" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2); Ord. of 4-2-02(2); Ord. of 4-25-02(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73EA16"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73EA2C">Sec. 86-73.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73EA37" data-type="subtitle">On-Premises Operator Required.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EA4E" class="p1">An adult entertainment establishment shall have a designated person(s) to serve as an on-premises operator. The operator(s) shall be principally in charge of the establishment and shall be located on the premises during all operating hours.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EA5F" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73EAAD"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73EABC">Sec. 86-74.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73EAC6" data-type="subtitle">Application Process and Qualifications.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EADD" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Process.</i> Any person, association, partnership or corporation desiring to obtain a license to operate, engage in, conduct, or carry on any adult entertainment establishment in the unincorporated areas of the county shall make application to the licensing and revenue manager of the county. Such application shall be made on forms furnished by the county, shall be made in the name of the adult entertainment establishment by an applicant who is a natural person and an agent of the adult entertainment establishment and shall include the name(s) of the operator(s) as defined herein and of the owner(s) as defined herein. If the adult entertainment establishment is a corporation, then the agent for purposes of making application for a license hereunder shall be an officer of the corporation. If the adult entertainment establishment is a partnership, the agent for such purposes shall be a general partner. At the time of submitting such application, a nonrefundable fee payable in cash or by certified check in the amount of $300.00 shall be paid to the licensing and revenue manager to defray, in part, the cost of investigation and report required by this article. The licensing and revenue manager shall issue a receipt showing that such application fee has been paid. The application for license does not authorize the operation of, engaging in, conduct or carrying on of any adult entertainment establishment.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EAFD" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Contents.</i> Each application for an adult entertainment establishment license shall contain the following information:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EB16" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">The full true name and any other names used by the applicant, the operator(s) and owner(s);</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EB2D" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">The present address and telephone number of the applicant, the operator(s) and owner(s);</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EB44" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">The previous addresses of the applicant, the operator(s) and the owner(s), if any, for a period five years immediately prior to the date of the application and the dates of residence at each;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EB5C" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Acceptable written proof that the applicant, the operator(s) and the owner(s) are at least 18 years of age;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EB74" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">The operator(s)' height, weight, color of eyes and hair and date and place of birth;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EB8B" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Two photographs of the operator(s) at least two inches by two inches taken within the last six months;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EBA2" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">The business, occupation or employment history of the applicant, the operator(s) and owner(s) for the five years immediately preceding the date of application;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EBBB" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">The business license history of the adult entertainment establishment seeking a license and whether such establishment, in previous operations in this or any other location under license, has had such license or permit for an adult entertainment business or similar type of business revoked or suspended, the reason therefor, and the business activity or occupation subsequent to such action of revocation or suspension;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EBD4" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(9)</span>
            <span class="li">If the application is made on behalf of a corporation, the name of the corporation, exactly as shown in its articles of incorporation or charter, together with the place and date of incorporation. If the application is on behalf of a limited partnership, a copy of the certificate of limited partnership filed with the county clerk shall be provided. If one or more of the partners is a corporation, the provisions of this subsection pertaining to corporations shall apply;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EBEF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(10)</span>
            <span class="li">The names and addresses of the owner and lessor of the real property upon which the adult entertainment establishment is to be operated, engaged in, conducted or carried on and a copy of the lease or rental agreement;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EC0A" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(11)</span>
            <span class="li">With respect to the applicant, the operator(s) and the owner(s), all convictions, (excluding misdemeanor traffic violations unrelated to driving under the influence of drugs or alcohol) within the past five years, including a complete description of the crime or violation, the date of the crime or violation, date of conviction (including plea of guilty or nolo contendere), jurisdiction and any disposition, including any fine or sentence imposed and whether the terms of disposition have been fully completed. Each person required to disclose convictions hereunder shall also provide a signed and notarized consent, on forms prescribed by the Georgia Crime Information Center, authorizing the release of his or her criminal records to the permits unit of the county police department.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EC29" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(12)</span>
            <span class="li">A complete set of fingerprints of the applicant and the operator(s);</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EC41" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(13)</span>
            <span class="li">If the person or business entity on whose behalf application for a license is doing business under a trade name, a copy of the trade name as properly recorded. If the application is made on behalf of a corporation, a copy of its authority to do business in the state, including articles of incorporation, trade name affidavit, if any, and last annual report, if any;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EC5A" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(14)</span>
            <span class="li">At least three character references for the applicant, the operator(s) and owner(s) from individuals who are in no way related to the applicant or any operator(s) or owner(s) and who are not or will not benefit financially in any way from the application if the license is granted. The county shall prepare forms consistent with the provisions of this subsection for the applicant, the operator(s) and owner(s), who shall submit all character references on such forms;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EC73" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(15)</span>
            <span class="li">The address of the premises where the adult entertainment establishment will be operated, engaged in, conducted, or carried on;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EC8B" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(16)</span>
            <span class="li">A plat by a registered engineer or a registered land surveyor, licensed by the state, showing the location of the proposed premises where the adult entertainment establishment will be operated, engaged in, conducted or carried on in relation to the neighborhood, the surrounding zoning, its proximity to any residential area, church, school, public park or children's day care facility, establishment selling alcoholic beverages or malt beverages and wine or other adult entertainment establishment;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B97AA" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(17)</span>
            <span class="li">Each application for an adult entertainment establishment license shall be verified and acknowledged under oath to be true and correct by:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73ECC3" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">a.</span>
            <span class="li">If application is made on behalf of an individual, the individual;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73ED13" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">b.</span>
            <span class="li">If application is made on behalf of a partnership, by a general partner;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B97B9" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">c.</span>
            <span class="li">If application is made on behalf of a corporation, by the president of the corporation;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73ED65" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">d.</span>
            <span class="li">If application is made on behalf of any other organization or association, by the chief administrative official.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73ED90" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Appearance by applicant.</i> The applicant shall personally appear before the licensing and revenue manager and produce proof that a nonrefundable application fee, in an amount established by resolution of the board of commissioners, has been paid and shall present the application containing the aforementioned and described information.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EDB0" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(d)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Investigation; standards for granting of license.</i> The county shall have 30 days from the date of actual receipt of the application to investigate the facts provided in the application and the background of the applicant, the operator(s) and owner(s). The licensing and revenue manager of the county shall stamp the date of actual receipt of each application on the first page thereof and notify the applicant of the actual receipt of the application within five business days of actual receipt of such application. The licensing and revenue manager of the county shall approve or deny any application for an adult entertainment establishment license within 30 days of actual receipt of such application. The application for an adult entertainment establishment license shall be granted if the licensing and revenue manager finds:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EDCD" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">The required $300.00 investigative fee has been paid;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EDE5" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">The applicant has not made a material misrepresentation in the application;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EDFC" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Neither the applicant nor any of the operator(s) or owner(s) has been convicted or pled guilty or entered a plea of nolo contendere to any crime involving keeping a place of prostitution, pandering, pimping, public indecency, prostitution, sodomy, solicitation of sodomy, masturbation for hire, sexual battery, rape, child molestation, enticing a child for indecent purposes, or any offense included in the definition of a "criminal offense against a victim who is a minor" as defined in O.C.G.A. § 42-1-12 within a period of five years. For purposes of this article, a conviction or plea of guilty or nolo contendere shall be ignored as to any offense for which the applicant was allowed to avail himself of the Georgia First Offender Act unless the applicant is later adjudicated guilty of having violated the terms of his first offender treatment;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EE19" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Neither the applicant nor any of the operator(s) or owner(s) has had an adult entertainment establishment license or other similar license or permit revoked for cause by this county or any other county or municipality located in or out of this state prior to the date of application within the preceding five years;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EE32" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">The building, structure, equipment and location of the premises of the adult entertainment establishment as proposed by the applicant would comply with all applicable laws, including but not limited to health, zoning, distance, fire and safety requirements and standards;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EE4B" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">The applicant is at least 18 years of age;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EE62" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">On the date the business for which a license is required herein commences, and thereafter, there will be an operator(s) as defined herein on the premises at all times during which the business is open;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EE81" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">The proposed premises will be located at least the minimum distances set forth in this article from any residential use, church, school, public park or children's daycare facility or establishment licensed to sell alcoholic beverages or malt beverages and wine for consumption on the premises, or another adult entertainment establishment; and</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EE9B" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(9)</span>
            <span class="li">The grant of such license will not cause a violation of and will not be in conflict with this article or any other law, ordinance or regulation, of the county, the state or the United States.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EEB3" class="p1">The licensing and revenue manager of the county shall deny the application for an adult entertainment establishment license if the application fails to meet any requirement contained in the county's ordinance regulating adult entertainment establishments.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EEC6" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2); Ord. of 4-25-02(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73EEE0"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73EEEE">Sec. 86-75.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73EEF8" data-type="subtitle">Regulation of Adult Entertainment Establishments.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EF0F" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Location.</i> No adult entertainment establishment shall be located:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EF27" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Within 1,000 feet of any parcel of land that falls within any of the following zoning districts as defined by the 1985 Zoning Resolution of Gwinnett County and the official zoning map of the county: RA-200, R-140, R-100, R-75, R-60, R-TH, R-ZT, RM, RMD, RM-6, RM-8, RM-10, RM-13, RL, MH, or MHS;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EF43" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Within 1,000 feet of any parcel of land on which a church, school, college campus, public park or children's day care facility is located;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EF5B" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Within 500 feet of any parcel of land upon which any establishment authorized to sell alcoholic beverages or malt beverages and wine for consumption on the premises is located;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EF72" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">In any zoning district other than a C-2 or C-3 commercial district; or</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EF8A" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Within 1,000 feet of any parcel of land upon which another adult entertain establishment regulated or defined hereunder is located.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EFA3" class="p1">For purposes of this section, distance shall be by airline measurement from property line, using the closest points on the property lines of the parcels of land involved. The term "parcel of land" means any quantity of land capable of being described by location and boundary, designated and used or to be used as a unit.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73EFB5" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Adult entertainment establishment employees.</i>
            </span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F05E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Qualifications.</i> Employees of an adult entertainment establishment shall be not less than 18 years of age. No employee employed as an adult entertainer shall have been convicted of an offense described in section 86-74(d)(3) of this article within the five years immediately preceding the proposed employment at or by an adult entertainment establishment. Any adult entertainer who is convicted of any such crimes while employed as an adult entertainer shall not thereafter work on any licensed premises for a period of five years from the date of such conviction, unless a longer time is ordered by a court of competent jurisdiction. The term "licensed premises" shall mean the premises where an adult entertainment establishment for which a license is obtained pursuant to this article operates, conducts or carries on its business. The term "convicted" shall include an adjudication of guilt or a plea of guilty or nolo contendere or the forfeiture of a bond when charged with a crime in a court of competent jurisdiction.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F0BA" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Permit for employment.</i> Before any person may work as an adult entertainer on a licensed premises, as defined in subsection (1), he or she shall file a notice with the county police permits unit of his or her intended employment on forms supplied by the county police permits unit and shall receive a permit for such employment from the county police permits unit. The prospective employee shall supply a signed and notarized consent, on forms prescribed by the Georgia Crime Information Center, authorizing the release of his or her criminal records to the county police department. The prospective employee shall also provide a list of all of his or her convictions of offenses described in subsection 86-74(d)(3) herein (including pleas of nolo contendere) within the past five years. The county police permits unit shall approve or deny the permit within 15 days of the application. If the prospective employee is found to meet the requirements of this subsection (b), and upon payment of the permit fee, the county police department shall issue a permit approving such employment within 48 hours. Upon receipt of a permit, the employee may begin working on the licensed premises. If approval is denied, the county police department shall provide the prospective adult entertainer the reasons for the denial and the prospective employee may, within ten days of said denial, appeal to the licensing and revenue board of appeals which shall uphold or reverse the decision within 30 days of such appeal. If the police permits unit does not approve or deny an application for a license within 45 days of the date such application was received by the county police permits unit, then on the expiration of the 45th day: (1) the application shall be approved and the county police permits unit shall immediately issue the license for which application was made, and (2) the applicant shall have the right to begin operating in the manner allowed by the license for which application was made. The annual permit fee shall be $25.00.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F0DD" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Suspension or revocation of permit; procedure.</i> Violation by an adult entertainer of the provisions of this article and/or conviction of an offense described in section 86-74(d)(3) of this article shall subject an adult entertainer to suspension or revocation of the permit for employment. Whenever the licensing and revenue manager finds that reasonable grounds exist to suspend or revoke a permit for employment issued hereunder, the licensing and revenue manager shall schedule a hearing before the licensing and revenue board of appeals to consider such action and shall notify the employee at least 20 days prior to the hearing of the time and place of the hearing and the proposed action and grounds therefor. The employee shall be entitled to present evidence and cross-examine witnesses with or without legal counsel. The licensing and revenue board of appeals shall make its decision within ten days of the hearing and shall notify the employee promptly in writing. In the event that a permit for employment is suspended or revoked by the licensing and revenue board of appeals, a $50.00 appeal cost shall be assessed against the permit holder.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F0FB" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Independent contractors.</i> For the purpose of this article, independent contractors working as adult entertainers shall be considered as employees and shall be required to satisfy the provisions of this article relating to employees of adult entertainment establishments, regardless of the business relationship with the owner or licensee of any adult entertainment establishment.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F115" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Hours of operation.</i> An adult entertainment establishment may be open only between the hours of 8:00 a.m. and 2:00 a.m.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F131" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(d)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Display of licenses.</i> An adult entertainment establishment licensee shall conspicuously display the license required by this article.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F149" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(e)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Performance area.</i> All dancing by adult entertainers at adult entertainment establishments shall occur on a platform intended for that purpose which is raised at least 18 inches from the level of the floor.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F162" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(f)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Lighting.</i> All areas of an adult entertainment establishment licensed hereunder shall be fully lighted at all times patrons are present. Full lighting shall mean illumination equal to 3.5 footcandles per square foot.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F17A" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(g)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Covering of windows and doors.</i> All adult entertainment which is licensed and permitted by this article shall be carried on inside a closed building with all windows and doors covered so that the activities carried on inside cannot be viewed from the immediate areas surrounding the outside of the building.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F193" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2); Ord. of 4-25-02(2); Amd. of 10-21-03(5), §§ 1, 2)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F1AD"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F1BB">Sec. 86-76.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73F1C5" data-type="subtitle">Conduct or Activities Prohibited.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F1DC" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Advertising without license.</i> No person, partnership, corporation or other entity shall advertise or cause to be advertised an adult entertainment establishment without a valid adult entertainment establishment license issued pursuant to this article.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F1F5" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Employment of minors or unpermitted persons.</i> No adult entertainment establishment licensee shall employ or contract with a person under the age of 18 years or an adult entertainer who has not obtained a permit pursuant to this article.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F20E" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Sale, consumption of alcohol.</i> No adult entertainment establishment licensee shall serve, sell, distribute or suffer the consumption or possession of any alcoholic beverages, malt beverages or wine or controlled substance upon the premises of the licensee.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F22D" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(d)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Contact between patrons, employees.</i> No dancing or other performance by an adult entertainer at an adult entertainment establishment shall occur closer than four feet to any patron. No patron, customer or guest shall be permitted to touch, caress or fondle any specified anatomical area of or any part of the body or clothing of any adult entertainer. No patron shall directly pay or give any gratuity to any adult entertainer. No adult entertainer shall solicit any pay or gratuity from any patron.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F2A2" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(e)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Engaging in specified sexual activities prohibited.</i> No adult entertainer, other employee, patron or other person at an adult entertainment establishment shall be allowed to engage in any specified sexual activity as defined herein on the premises of any adult entertainment establishment.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F2BD" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(f)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Public indecency prohibited.</i> No adult entertainer, other employee, patron or other person at an adult entertainment establishment shall, while on the premises of an adult entertainment establishment, commit the offense of public indecency as defined in O.c.G.A. § 16-6-8.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F2D6" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F2EF"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F2FD">Sec. 86-77.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73F307" data-type="subtitle">Penalty for Violation.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F31F" class="p1">Any person violating any of the provisions of section 86-76 of this article shall be guilty of a misdemeanor, punishable by a fine not to exceed $1,000.00 per violation or by imprisonment for a period not to exceed 60 days, or both. Each day of operation in violation of this article shall be deemed a separate offense.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F330" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F34A"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F358">Sec. 86-78.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73F362" data-type="subtitle">Unlawful Operation Declared Nuisance.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F37B" class="p1">Any adult entertainment establishment operated, conducted or maintained contrary to the provisions of this article shall be and the same is hereby declared to be unlawful and a public nuisance. The county may, in addition to or in lieu of prosecuting a criminal action hereunder, commence an action or actions, proceeding or proceedings for abatement, removal or enjoinment thereof in the manner provided by law. It may take such other steps and shall apply to such court or courts as may have jurisdiction to grant such relief as will abate or remove such adult entertainment establishment and restrain and enjoin any person from operating, engaging in, conducting or carrying on an adult entertainment establishment contrary to the provisions of this article.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B985B" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F3A8"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F3B5">Sec. 86-79.</h2>
	           <p id="x156991AC270" data-type="subtitle">Conditions of Adult Entertainment Establishment.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F3D6" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Cleaning of licensed premises.</i> All adult entertainment establishments shall be kept in a clean, sanitary condition, and shall be in full compliance with all applicable ordinances and regulations of the county and the state.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F3EE" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Inspection of licensed premises.</i> The county fire marshal shall have the authority to regularly inspect adult entertainment establishments, to determine compliance with and enforce all applicable fire, health and other codes of the county.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F407" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Inspection for unsanitary or unsafe conditions.</i> The county police department shall have the authority to periodically inspect adult entertainment establishments to determine compliance with and enforce all provisions of this article and other applicable ordinances, regulations and laws.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F41F" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F439"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F447">Sec. 86-80.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73F451" data-type="subtitle">Denial, Suspension or Revocation of License; Hearing.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F468" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Grounds.</i>
            </span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F47F" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">A license may be denied to persons or entities that have submitted an incomplete application or that have failed to satisfy any of the requirements of the county's ordinance regulating adult entertainment establishments found at sections 86-70 through 86-85 of this Code.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F497" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Any of the following shall be grounds for suspension or revocation of a license:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F4AF" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">a.</span>
            <span class="li">The making of any statement on an application for a license issued hereunder which is material and is later found to be false;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F4C7" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">b.</span>
            <span class="li">Violation of any of the regulations or prohibitions of this article;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F4DE" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">c.</span>
            <span class="li">With respect to the applicant, operator(s) and owner(s), conviction of or a plea of guilty or nolo contendere to any of the crimes which would make such person or adult entertainment establishment ineligible to hold a license under section 86-74(d) above.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F4FA" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Denial; procedure.</i> Within 30 days of actual receipt of an application for an adult entertainment establishment license, the licensing and revenue manager shall either approve or deny the application. In no event shall the licensing and revenue manager's decision whether to approve or deny the adult entertainment establishment license application be withheld for more than 30 days after actual receipt of the application. In the event that such an application is held without decision for a period of more than 30 days, however, the license application shall be deemed approved, and expressive conduct may begin immediately notwithstanding the fact that no license has been issued. The director of the county's finance department shall issue an adult entertainment establishment license to an applicant who informs the director of finance of the fact that an application has been submitted, but no decision has been made thereon for a period of more than 30 days following actual receipt of the application. Notwithstanding the fact that the license provided by this sentence shall not be a prerequisite to the commencement of business operations contemplated by the application, the director of county's finance department shall issue an adult entertainment establishment license under such circumstances within three business days of actual receipt of written notice by the applicant of such circumstances. In the event that the licensing and revenue manager denies an application for an adult entertainment establishment license, notice of such denial shall be delivered to the applicant in person or by certified mail within five business days of such denial. Any person aggrieved by any decision of the county, its officials, employees or agents pursuant to this article, may seek review of such decision by filing an appropriate pleading in the superior court of the county or any other court of competent jurisdiction including, but not limited to, a mandamus petition pursuant to O.C.G.A. §§ 9-6-20—9-6-28. Any person aggrieved by any decision of the county, its officials, employees, or agents pursuant to this article may also seek review of such decision by filing a petition for writ of certiorari or an appeal to the superior court pursuant to the provisions of Section 1609 of the 1985 Zoning Resolution of Gwinnett County.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F555" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Suspension or revocation; procedure.</i> Whenever the licensing and revenue board of appeals finds reasonable grounds exist to suspend or revoke a license issued hereunder, the board shall schedule a hearing to consider such suspension or revocation and shall, at least 20 days prior to the hearing, notify the licensee of the time and date of the hearing and the proposed action and the grounds therefor. The licensee shall be entitled to present evidence and cross-examine any witnesses at the hearing, with or without legal counsel. The licensing and revenue board of appeals shall make its decision within ten days of the hearing and shall notify the licensee in writing within five business days of the decision.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F571" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2); Ord. of 4-25-02(2); Amd. of 10-21-03(5), § 4)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F58B"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F598">Sec. 86-81.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73F5A3" data-type="subtitle">Miscellaneous.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F5BB" class="p1">Nothing contained in this article shall be deemed to permit or condone any activity whatsoever which is otherwise found to be obscene, lewd or illegal under applicable code, regulation or statute which provides any prohibition upon nudity or sexual activity. Further the activities and uses which are regulated and permitted by this article shall only be allowed if they are not obscene or lewd and not in violation of any other such prohibitions on nudity or sexual activity.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F5CD" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F5E9"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F5F9">Sec. 86-82.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73F603" data-type="subtitle">Severability.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F61C" class="p1">If any portion or subsection of this article or its application to any person or circumstance is held invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder or application to other persons or circumstances shall not be affected.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F62D" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="xD61FB0B98A2"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F66B">Sec. 86-83.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73F677" data-type="subtitle">Automatic License Forfeiture for Nonuse.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F691" class="p1">Any holder of any license hereunder who shall for a period of three consecutive months after the license has been issued cease to operate the business and sale of the product or products authorized shall after the said three-month period automatically forfeit the license without the necessity of any further action.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F6A3" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F6C0"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F6CE">Sec. 86-84.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73F6D9" data-type="subtitle">Repeal of Conflicting Provisions.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F6F2" class="p1">All resolutions or ordinances, or parts thereof, in conflict with this article are hereby repealed, provided, however, that the provisions of sections 18-291 through 18-306 of this Code, adopted on or about July 17, 2001, shall remain in full force and effect and shall be applied in a manner consistent with the provisions of sections 86-70 through 86-85 of this Code. The provisions of sections 18-291 through 18-306 of the Gwinnett County Code of Ordinances are hereby amended to add language consistent with the amendments to this article adopted on April 25, 2002. In addition, the provisions of an ordinance regulating video stores within unincorporated Gwinnett County adopted on or about August 7, 2001, shall remain in full force and effect and shall be applied in a manner consistent with the terms of this article.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F706" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2); Ord. of 4-25-02(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F722"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="xD61FB0B98B8">Sec. 86-85.</h2>
	           <p id="xD61FB0B98B9" data-type="subtitle">Physical Layout of Establishment.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F752" class="p1">Any adult entertainment establishment having available for customers, patrons or members any booth, room, or cubicle for the private viewing of any adult entertainment must comply with the following requirements:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F763" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Access.</i> Each booth, room or cubicle shall be totally accessible to and from aisles and public areas of the establishment, and shall be unobstructed by any curtain, door, lock, or other control-type or view-obstructing devices or materials.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F77F" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Construction.</i> Every booth, room or cubicle shall meet the following construction requirements:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F797" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">a.</span>
            <span class="li">Each booth, room or cubicle shall be separated from adjacent booths, rooms and cubicles and any nonpublic areas by a wall.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F7AE" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">b.</span>
            <span class="li">Have at least one side totally open to a public lighted area or aisle so that there is an unobstructed view of anyone occupying the booth from the area in which the cash register for the adult entertainment establishment is located.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F7C7" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">c.</span>
            <span class="li">All walls shall be solid and without openings, extended from the floor to a height of not less than six feet and be light colored, nonabsorbent, smooth-textured and easily cleanable.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F7E6" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">d.</span>
            <span class="li">The floor must be light colored, nonabsorbent, smooth-textured and easily cleaned.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F7FE" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">e.</span>
            <span class="li">The lighting level of each booth, room or cubicle when not in use shall be a minimum of ten candles at all times, as measured from the floor.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B98CF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Occupants.</i> Only one individual shall occupy a booth, room or cubicle at any time. No occupant of same shall engage in any type of sexual activity, cause any bodily discharge or litter while in the booth, room or cubicle. No individual shall damage or deface any portion of the booth, room or cubicle.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F835" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 8-7-01(2))</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F851"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F85F">Secs. 86-86—86-99.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73F86A" data-type="subtitle" data-widowtype="no">Reserved.</p>
         </header>

      </section>

   </section>

   <section id="x85D3CE73F893"
            class="article"
            data-type="sect1"
            data-pubmap="level3">
      <header>
	        <h1 id="x85D3CE73F8A1">Article V.</h1>
	        <p id="xD61FB0B98DE" data-type="subtitle">Signs</p>
      </header>

      <section id="x85D3CE73F8C5"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73F8D3">Sec. 86-100.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73F8DD" data-type="subtitle">Findings and Purpose.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F8F7" class="p1">The board of commissioners finds that signs provide an important medium through which persons may convey a variety of noncommercial and commercial messages. However, left completely unregulated, signs can become a threat to public safety as a traffic hazard and a detriment to property values and to the county's general public welfare, as well as create an aesthetic nuisance. By enacting this article, the board of commissioners intends to:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F93F" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Balance the rights of persons to convey their messages through signs and the right of the public to be protected against the unrestricted proliferation of signs;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F96E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Protect the public health, safety, and welfare of the citizens and others within the county;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F996" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Reduce traffic hazards, pedestrian hazards, and other hazards;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F9AF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Promote and maintain the aesthetic qualities of the county;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F9C9" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Protect property values by minimizing the possible adverse effects and visual blight caused by signs;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73F9E6" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Promote economic development;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9901" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">Ensure the fair and consistent enforcement of sign regulations;</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FA25" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">Promote the stated purposes of the Gwinnett County Zoning Ordinance, as amended, which are expressly incorporated herein; and</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FA3E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(9)</span>
            <span class="li">Promote the stated purposes of the Standard Building Code, as adopted and modified by the county, which are expressly incorporated herein.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FA59" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE73FA77"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE73FA88">Sec. 86-101.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE73FA94" data-type="subtitle">Definitions.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FAAD" class="p1">Except as specifically defined herein, all words used in this article shall be as defined in the most recent edition of The Illustrated Book of Development Definitions (Rutgers). Words not defined herein or in the above book shall be construed to have the meaning given by common and ordinary use, and shall be interpreted within the context of the sentence, section and article in which they occur.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FABF" class="p1">For the purpose of this article, certain words or terms used herein shall be defined as follows:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FACF" class="p1">Words used in the singular include the plural and words used in the plural include the singular.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FAE1" class="p1">Words used in the present tense include the future tense.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FAF3" class="p1">The word "erected" includes the words "constructed", "moved", "located" or "relocated".</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FB06" class="p1">The word "lot" includes the word "plot" or "parcel".</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FB1B" class="p1">The word "map" or "zoning map" means the Zoning Map of Gwinnett County, Georgia.</p>

         <p id="x156991AC283" class="p1">The word "person" includes the words "individuals", "firms", "partnerships", "corporations", "associations", "governmental bodies" and all other legal entities.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FB3D" class="p1">The word "shall" is always mandatory and never discretionary.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FB4F" class="p1">The words "used" or occupied include the words "intended, arranged or designed to be used or occupied."</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FB60" class="p1">
            <i>Accessory ground sign</i> means a permanently affixed sign which is wholly independent of a building for support, and which is accessory and subordinate to a primary ground sign.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FB74" class="p1">
            <i>Accessory structure</i> means a structure detached from a principal building on the same lot and customarily incidental and subordinate to the principal building or use.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FB85" class="p1">
            <i>Accessory use</i> means a use of land or of a building or portion thereof customarily incidental and subordinate to the principal use of the land or building and located on the same lot with such principal use.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FB9D" class="p1">
            <i>Aggregate sign area</i> means the combined sign surface area of all signs on a lot, excluding the area of one face of all double-faced signs. Noncommercial flags and banners are excluded from any determination of aggregate sign area.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FBAF" class="p1">
            <i>Animated sign</i> means any sign or portion thereof involving motion, flashing, blinking, rotation or varying light intensity.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FBC0" class="p1">
            <i>Banner</i> means a piece of fabric or similar material which is attached to a pole, enclosed in a frame, or mounted as a temporary sign device.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FBD1" class="p1">
            <i>Billboard.</i> See "oversized signs."</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FBE2" class="p1">
            <i>Building</i> means any structure attached to the ground which has a roof and which is designed for the shelter, housing or enclosure of persons, animals, or property of any kind.</p>

         <p id="x156991AC285" class="p1">
            <i>Building space, gross</i> means the sum of the gross horizontal areas of the several floors of a building from the exterior face of the exterior walls, or from the centerline of a wall separating two buildings, but excluding any space where the floor to ceiling height is less than six feet.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FC07" class="p1">
            <i>County</i> shall mean Gwinnett County, Georgia.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FC19" class="p1">
            <i>Department</i> shall mean the county department of planning and development, and its subordinate divisions, sections and units.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FC2E" class="p1">
            <i>Director</i> shall mean the director of the department of planning and development, who may act through designee(s).</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FC42" class="p1">
            <i>Double faced sign</i> means a sign which has two display areas against each other or where the interior angle formed by the display areas is 60 degrees or less, where one face is designed to be seen from one direction and the other face from another direction.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FC54" class="p1">
            <i>Entrance sign</i> means a permanent sign located at the public street or private driveway entrance to a residential development, residential subdivision development or nonresidential subdivision development.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FC6B" class="p1">
            <i>Flag</i> means a piece of fabric or other flexible material solely containing distinctive colors, patterns, standards, words or emblems used as the symbol of an organization or entity.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FC7D" class="p1">
            <i>Flashing sign.</i> See "animated sign."</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FC91" class="p1">
            <i>Graduation banner.</i> A banner that provides information about a student's or students' graduation from any school or college.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FCA5" class="p1">
            <i>Ground sign height</i> means the distance in vertical feet from the elevation of the adjacent dedicated public street, edge of pavement, to the highest point of the sign structure. For property with an elevation higher than the adjacent public street, the height shall be measured from ground level at base of sign to the highest point of the sign structure. The ground shall not be altered for the sole purpose of providing additional sign height.</p>

         <p id="x156991AC287" class="p1">
            <i>Indirectly illuminated sign</i> means a sign illuminated by an external light source directed primarily toward such sign.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9948" class="p1">
            <i>Interior project directional sign</i> means a sign located no closer than 100 feet from the exterior public street entrance of a nonresidential project, at a street intersection or along a private driveway within the project. The purpose of this sign is to provide more definitive directional information concerning the whereabouts of the tenants.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FD1E" class="p1">
            <i>Internally illuminated sign</i> means a sign illuminated by an internal light source.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FD33" class="p1">
            <i>Landscape strip</i> means land area located within the boundary of a lot and required to be set aside and used for landscaping upon which only limited encroachments are authorized.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FD45" class="p1">
            <i>Lot</i> means a designated parcel, tract, or area of land established by plat, subdivision, or as otherwise permitted by law, to be separately owned, used, developed, or built upon.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9956" class="p1">
            <i>Monument-type sign</i> means a permanent ground sign designed so that the base of the sign face is flush with the supporting base, and the supporting base is flush with the ground and extends the full width of the sign face.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FD6E" class="p1">
            <i>Multi-faced sign</i> means a sign structure with more than two sign faces situated so that each sign face is facing a different direction.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FD80" class="p1">
            <i>Nonconforming sign</i> means any sign lawfully existing on the effective date of this article, or amendment thereto, that renders such sign nonconforming because it does not conform to all the standards and regulations of the adopted or amended ordinance.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FD91" class="p1">
            <i>Oversized or billboard sign</i> means a ground sign which exceeds 30 feet in sign height and/or 300 square feet of sign surface area.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B995D" class="p1">
            <i>Parkway</i> means a divided or undivided classified roadway, including:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FDB5" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">University Parkway (Ga. Hwy. 316).</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FDCD" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Peachtree Parkway (Ga. Hwy. 141).</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FDEA" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Grayson Parkway (Ga. Hwy. 84).</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FE02" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Ronald Reagan Parkway.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FE1B" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Sugarloaf Parkway.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FE32" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Hamilton Mill Parkway.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FE4A" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">Riverside Parkway.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FE6C" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">Northbrook Parkway.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FE8C" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(9)</span>
            <span class="li">Lakes Parkway.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FEA8" class="p1">
            <i>Planned commercial/office/industrial development</i> means a contiguous area or subdivision of land, planned and maintained as a single entity and containing one or more structures to accommodate retail, service, commercial, office or industrial uses, or a combination of such uses, and appurtenant common areas and accessory uses incidental to the predominant uses (i.e., office park, shopping center, industrial park).</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B997A" class="p1">
            <i>Portable sign</i> means any sign which is manifestly designed to be transported, including by trailer or on its own wheels, even though the wheels of such sign may be removed and the remaining chassis or support constructed without wheels is converted to an "A" or "T" frame sign or attached temporarily or permanently to the ground.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FEDA" class="p1">
            <i>Primary ground sign</i> means a permanently affixed sign which is wholly independent of a building for support.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B997E" class="p1">
            <i>Principal use</i> means the primary or predominant purpose for which a lot is occupied and/or used.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FEFD" class="p1">
            <i>Projecting sign</i> means a sign projecting more than six inches from the outside wall or walls of any building upon which it is located.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FF11" class="p1">
            <i>Road frontage</i> means the distance on which a parcel of land adjoins a public street or public road right-of-way dedicated to and accepted by the county for vehicular traffic or over which the county may hold a prescriptive easement for public access, and including designated and numbered U.S. and state highways.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FF2B" class="p1">
            <i>Roof sign</i> means a sign projecting over the coping of a flat roof, or wholly or partially over the ridge of a gable, hip or gambrel roof, and supported by or attached to said roof.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FF4D" class="p1">
            <i>Sign, sidewalk or sandwich</i> means a moveable sign not secured or attached to the ground or surface upon which it is located.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B998A" class="p1">
            <i>Sign</i> means an object, device, display, or structure, or part thereof, which is used to advertise, identify, display, direct, or attract attention to an object, person, institution, organization, business, product, service, event or location by any means, including words, letters, figures, design, symbols, fixtures, colors, illumination, or projected images. Any sign provided for in any zoning district may contain noncommercial messages. The following shall not be included within the definition of "sign" and shall not be regulated as such: Any item encompassed by Article VI, Section 600 of the Gwinnett County Zoning Resolution of 1985, as amended and allowed in "front yards."</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FF77" class="p1">
            <i>Sign face</i> means the area or display surface of a sign which is used for the message.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FF89" class="p1">
            <i>Sign, off-premises</i> means a real estate sign which advertises or directs attention to property other than on the premises on which the sign is located.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FF9A" class="p1">
            <i>Sign structure</i> means poles, beams, columns, posts, foundations, or other means providing structural support for the sign surface area to which the sign is affixed.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FFAC" class="p1">
            <i>Sign surface area</i> means the smallest square, rectangle, triangle, circle or combination thereof, which encompasses the entire sign inclusive of any border and trim, but excluding the base, apron, supports, and other structural members.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FFBF" class="p1">
            <i>Special use permit</i> is a use listed in the zoning resolution as being permitted if it meets stated conditions and is approved by the board of commissioners of the county.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9995" class="p1">
            <i>Streamer</i> means any long, narrow flag, banner, tinsel or roping which is hung or strung from any structure to another structure or the ground.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE73FFE3" class="p1">
            <i>Structure</i> means anything constructed or erected on the ground or attached to something on the ground.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9999" class="p1">
            <i>Subdivision directional sign</i> means an off-premises sign which provides directions to property for sale, lease or rent. Subdivision directional signs are placed at intersections, directing traffic to a specific project(s).</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740015" class="p1">
            <i>Temporary sign</i> means a sign of a nonpermanent nature.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740026" class="p1">
            <i>Trailer sign</i> means any sign which is mounted on wheels and which may be moved from one location to another.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740038" class="p1">
            <i>Wall sign</i> means a sign applied to or mounted to the wall or surface of a building or structure, the display surface which does not project more than six inches from the outside wall of such a building or structure.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74004C" class="p1">
            <i>Weekend directional sign</i> means an off-premises sign which provides directions to property for sale, lease or rent. Weekend directional signs may be erected from Friday 3:00 p.m. until Sunday 11:59 p.m., and direct traffic to a specific project. Note: Weekend direction signs are prohibited by section 86-108.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74009F" class="p1">
            <i>Window sign</i> means a sign installed flush with the interior or exterior of a window and intended to be viewed from the outside. Any sign prohibited by section 86-108 shall not be allowed as a window sign.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7400B3" class="p1">
            <i>Yard, front</i> means an open, unoccupied space on the same lot with a principal building or use, extending the full width of the lot and located between the street line and the front line of the building projected parallel to the street to the side lines of the lot. Corner lots shall be considered to have two front yards.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7400C8" class="p1">
            <i>Yard, rear</i> means an open space on the same lot with a principal building or use, unoccupied except by an accessory building or use, extending the full width of the lot and located between the rear line of the lot and the rear line of the building or use projected to the side lines of the lot.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7400DB" class="p1">
            <i>Yard, side</i> means an open, unoccupied space on the same lot with a principal building or use, located between the building or use and the side line of the lot and extending from the rear line of the front yard to the front line of the rear yard.</p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B99B2" class="p1">
            <i>Zoning board of appeals</i> shall mean the zoning board of appeals of the county (see zoning resolution article XVI).</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74010D" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01; Res. No. SOA2003-001, 5-27-03; Res. No. SOA2008-001, 3-25-08; Amd. of 12-16-08, § 1)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE740128"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE740135">Sec. 86-102.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE740140" data-type="subtitle">General Provisions.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE74015B" class="p1">It shall be unlawful for any person to post, display, alter the structure, or erect a sign without a sign location permit or temporary sign permit. A change in the copy of a sign or advertising device shall not constitute an alteration.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740173" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE7401A3"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE7401B1">Sec. 86-103.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE7401BD" data-type="subtitle">Sign Permit Application.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE7401D6" class="p1">Applications for sign permits shall be submitted by the sign owner or their agent upon official forms furnished by the department. Applications shall be complete and shall include the following:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7401E8" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">The type of sign, and cost of sign construction.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74020F" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">The street address of the property upon which subject sign is to be located. In the absence of a street address, a method of location acceptable to the department shall be used.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740228" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">For ground signs: A site plan drawn to scale, showing the proposed location of all primary and accessory ground sign(s) on subject property. The site plan includes, at a minimum, a closed boundary survey of the property, gross acreage, the proposed sign location, street right-of-way lines, public or private easements, driveway locations and parking spaces.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740242" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Sign details, including a scaled elevation of the size and height and of the proposed sign from ground level and adjacent street level.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740264" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">The square foot area per sign and the aggregate square foot area if there is more than one sign face.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74028F" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">The gross building space of all building(s) on the property.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7402AB" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">The name(s) and address(es) of the owner(s) of the real property upon which the sign is to be located.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7402C6" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">Written consent of the property owner, or his agent, granting permission for the placement and/or maintenance of subject sign. The signature of consent may be electronic subject to the requirements of Georgia law.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7402DF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(9)</span>
            <span class="li">The name, address and phone number of the sign contractor.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740304" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01; Res. No. SOA2003-001, 5-27-03)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE740321"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE74032F">Sec. 86-104.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE740339" data-type="subtitle">Expiration Date.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE740354" class="p1">A sign location permit shall expire if the sign for which the permit was issued has not been erected, installed and completed within six months after the date of permit issuance, provided, however, that one six-month extension of the permit shall be granted if an additional permit extension fee has been paid prior to the expiration date of the initial permit.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740366" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE740387"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE740395">Sec. 86-105.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE7403A0" data-type="subtitle">Sign Permit Fees.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE7403B7" class="p1">A sign location permit or temporary sign permit shall not be issued until the appropriate application has been submitted and fees have been paid, as established by the board of commissioners.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7403C8" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE7403E4"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE7403F2">Sec. 86-106.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE7403FC" data-type="subtitle">Labels Required on Signs.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE74041A" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">For each wall or ground sign location permit, an official sticker bearing the same number as the permit will be issued. It shall be the duty of the permit holder or their agent to affix the sticker to the sign so it will be easily read from ground level. The absence of an official sticker shall be prima facie evidence that the sign has been, or is being, erected or installed in violation of the provisions of this article.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740434" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">For each temporary sign permit, the permit holder or, permit holder's agent shall keep the official permit on file at the premises as evidence of permit issuance. The absence of an official permit shall be prima facie evidence that the sign has been, or is being, displayed in violation of this ordinance.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74044D" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01; Res. No. SOA2003-001, 5-27-03)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE740467"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="xD61FB0B9A0C">Section 86-107.</h2>
	           <p id="xD61FB0B9A0D" data-type="subtitle">Nonconforming Signs.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE740499" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">The lawful use of a permanent sign existing at the time of the adoption of this article may be continued in nonconformance with the requirements of this article, except that the nonconforming sign shall not be enlarged, altered, modified, improved or rebuilt. A nonconforming sign may be repaired to the extent necessary to maintain it in a safe condition and neat and orderly appearance. A change in the advertising message on the sign shall not constitute an alteration or modification of the sign.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7404EA" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">No structural repair or change in shape, size or design, shall be permitted except to make a nonconforming sign comply with all requirements of this article or to render the sign structurally sound. Routine maintenance and changing of copy shall be permitted as long as such maintenance or changing of copy does not result in or change the shape, size, or design.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740507" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">A nonconforming sign structure may not be replaced by another nonconforming sign structure, except where changed conditions beyond the control of the owner warrant the signs repair.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74051F" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE74053A"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE740547">Sec. 86-108.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE740553" data-type="subtitle">Signs and Sign Devices Prohibited.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE74056C" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">The following types of signs or advertising devices are prohibited in all zoning districts of the county:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740585" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Roof signs.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74059D" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Streamers.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7405B4" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Portable, trailer, sidewalk, sandwich, curb, or "A"-type signs.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7405CB" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Multi-faced signs.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7405E5" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Animated signs, including but not limited to those involving motion, flashing, blinking, rotation or varying light intensity.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7405FF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs placed within public rights-of-way, except publicly owned, authorized or maintained signs which serve an official public purpose.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740619" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs erected by nailing, fastening or affixing the sign in any manner to any tree, rock, post, curb, utility pole, natural feature, official street sign or marker, traffic control sign or device, or other structure except as may be set forth herein.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740633" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">Any sign placed or erected on property without the permission of the owner.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74064C" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(9)</span>
            <span class="li">Weekend directional signs.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740667" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(10)</span>
            <span class="li">Individual or aggregate window signs exceeding 20 percent of the window area per building elevation.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74067F" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(11)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs which contain words, pictures, or statements which are obscene, as defined by O.C.G.A. § 16-12-80.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740698" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(12)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs which simulate an official traffic control device, warning sign, or regulatory sign or which hide from view any traffic control device, signal or public service sign.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7406B0" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(13)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs which emit or utilize in any manner any sound capable of being detected on any traveled road or highway by a person with normal hearing abilities.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7406C7" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(14)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs which interfere with road or highway visibility or obstruct or otherwise interfere with the safe and orderly movement of traffic or which otherwise pose a hazard to traffic due to structural deficiencies in the structure of such signs.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7406E1" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(15)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs which advertise any activity, service, or product prohibited by the laws or regulations of the United States or the state or by the ordinances or resolutions of the county. This section shall not prohibit signs promoting the legalization of any matter presently prohibited by federal, state, or local law.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7406FE" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(16)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs which obstruct any fire escape, any means of egress or ventilation or shall prevent free passage from one part of a roof to any other part thereof, as well as signs attached to any fire escape.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740717" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(17)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs which do not conform to applicable building and electrical codes.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740730" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(18)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs for which a permit is required that do not display the sign permit number and the name and address of the person responsible for erecting and maintaining the sign.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74074A" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(19)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs which are in violation of the rules and regulations of any zoning overlay district presently existing or as may later be enacted.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740764" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(20)</span>
            <span class="li">Any sign constructed of nondurable material including, but not limited to, paper, cardboard or flexible plastic that has been displayed for more than 60 days. Nothing herein shall prohibit such a sign from being replaced by an identical sign. This provision does not apply to temporary signs as governed by this article.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74077F" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(21)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs located on any substandard lot created after the enactment of this article, unless the substandard lot is created as the result of governmental action.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740797" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(22)</span>
            <span class="li">Abandoned commercial signs. Commercial signs (including sign structures) shall be deemed abandoned if the business, service or commercial transaction to which it relates has been discontinued for 90 days.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7407AF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(23)</span>
            <span class="li">Any sign that is structurally unsound, or is a hazard to traffic or pedestrians.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7407C8" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(24)</span>
            <span class="li">Dilapidated or neglected signs. A sign (including sign structure) will be dilapidated or neglected if it does not present a neat and orderly appearance, which may be manifested by the following: rust or holes on or in the sign or sign structure, or broken, missing, loose or bent parts, faded or flaking paint, nonoperative or partially nonoperative illuminating or mechanical devices or missing letters in sign copy.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7407E3" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01; Res. No. SOA2003-001, 5-27-03; Amd. of 12-16-08, § 2)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE7407FF"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE74080E">Sec. 86-109.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE740818" data-type="subtitle">Temporary Signs.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE740831" class="p1">The following types of signs or advertising devices shall be permitted only by issuance of a temporary sign permit allowing use of this type advertising for a period of 21 consecutive days. A temporary sign permit may not be issued for the same premises at less than three-month intervals. In no case shall the same premises be allowed a temporary sign permit more than four times in a 12-month period. A fee, as established by the board of commissioners, shall be paid for each temporary sign permit. Upon expiration of the temporary sign permit, the permittee shall remove the air or gas filled device, search light, or banner(s) including any temporary supporting structure.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74087C" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Air or gas filled devices not exceeding:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7408A2" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">a.</span>
            <span class="li">Twenty feet in height and 150 square feet of area in a nonresidential zoning district.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7408BF" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">b.</span>
            <span class="li">Four feet in height and 16 square feet of area in a residential zoning district.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7408D9" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Except as exempted under section 86-111, banners which display a message, logo, statement, or commercial message shall be regulated as follows:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7408F2" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">a.</span>
            <span class="li">Each banner shall not exceed 16 square feet.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74090D" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">b.</span>
            <span class="li">Each banner must be individually attached to a pole, mast, arm, or other structure.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74092B" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">c.</span>
            <span class="li">For any lot, banners shall be limited to one banner per public street frontage.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740945" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">d.</span>
            <span class="li">Banners must be maintained in good condition.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740960" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Search lights and similar devices.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9A8C" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01; Res. No. SOA2008-001, 3-25-08)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE740991"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE74099F">Sec. 86-110.</h2>
	           <p id="xD61FB0B9A91" data-type="subtitle">Flags.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE7409C6" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">All flags shall be displayed on purpose-built, professionally fabricated flagpoles, which may be vertical or mast-arm flagpoles. In nonresidential districts, flagpoles shall not exceed the allowed height provided for a structure or building in the applicable zoning district, or 50 feet, unless approved through the tall structure permit process. Flagpoles in residential districts shall not exceed 25 feet in height or the height of the primary structure on the lot, whichever is less.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7409E2" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">The maximum dimensions of any flag shall be proportional to the flagpole height. The hoist side of the flag shall not exceed 20 percent of the vertical height of the flagpole. In addition, flags are subject to the following limitations:</span>
         </p>

         <table id="x85D3CE740A0A">
            <caption/>
            <colgroup data-cols="2">
	              <col width="50.00%"/>
	              <col width="50.00%"/>
            </colgroup>

            <thead/>

            <tbody>
               <tr>
	                 <td>Pole Height</td>
	                 <td>Maximum Flag Size (total square feet)</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>Up to 30 feet</td>
	                 <td>30 square feet</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>30 to 50 feet</td>
	                 <td>60 square feet</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>50 feet or greater</td>
	                 <td>150 square feet</td>
               </tr>
            </tbody>
         </table>

         <p id="x85D3CE740AA9" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">Each lot or parcel shall be allowed a maximum of three flag poles.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9AAD" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(d)</span>
            <span class="li">A maximum of two flags shall be allowed per flagpole.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740ADA" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(e)</span>
            <span class="li">Flags displaying a logo, message, statement, or commercial message and banners not meeting the definition of a flag contained herein shall conform to all applicable ordinances pertaining to signs.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740AF3" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(f)</span>
            <span class="li">A vertical flagpole must be set back from all property boundaries a distance which is at least equal to the height of the flagpole.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740B0C" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(g)</span>
            <span class="li">Flags and flagpoles shall be maintained in good repair, and to the extent applicable shall be in compliance with the building code. Flagpoles with broken halyards shall not be used and flags which are torn or frayed shall not be displayed.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740B24" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(h)</span>
            <span class="li">On officially designated county, state, or federal holidays, there shall be no maximum flag size or number or other limitations on display.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740B3E" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(i)</span>
            <span class="li">This section shall not be construed to restrict the right to display eligible flags as banners or noncommercial signage as provided elsewhere in this article.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740B59" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(j)</span>
            <span class="li">A sign permit is not required for flags.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740B71" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01; Res. No. SOA2003-001, 5-27-03)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE740B8B"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE740B98">Sec. 86-111.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE740BA4" data-type="subtitle">Signs Exempt From Specified Provisions of This Article.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9AC6" class="p1">The following types of signs are exempt from the requirements of this article unless otherwise expressly prohibited under section 86-108. However, all of these signs shall abide by the height and setback requirements as specified in section 86-114A (Sign Table).</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740BCD" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Non-illuminated temporary freestanding signs (excluding banners which are regulated in accordance with section 86-109 and subsection 86-111(11)). For each residential or non-residential lot, the quantity of these signs shall be limited to either one sign that is 16 square feet in area or up to four signs with each of these signs limited to a maximum of four square feet in area. In addition, each sign shall not be greater than eight feet above the grade level of the adjacent street to which the sign is located or three feet above ground level, whichever is greater. These signs shall not be located within the public street right-of-way and shall be no closer than ten feet to the back of the curb of a public roadway.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740BE8" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs for the sole purpose of displaying street numbers as may be required by other ordinances and other signs required by law.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740C03" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs erected by, or on the order of, a public officer in the performance of his duty including but not limited to public notices, safety signs, danger signs, trespassing signs, traffic and street signs, memorial plaques and signs of historical interest.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740C2E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs on private property prohibiting trespassing in accordance with state law.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740C54" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Any sign not visible from public thoroughfares or any sign within a business, office, mall, or totally enclosed area.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740CC2" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Window signs not exceeding 20 percent of the available window space per building elevation.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740CF5" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">One official sign per road frontage, as required by the state, identifying vehicle emissions inspection stations licensed by the state.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740D25" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">Swinging or projecting signs not exceeding three square feet, or projecting more than four feet and attached under the eave or awning of a building above a business entrance.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740D48" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(9)</span>
            <span class="li">Signage on courtesy benches, trash receptacles, newspaper boxes, automated teller kiosks and phone booths, not exceeding eight square feet of sign area and not located within the required front yard setback for the zoning district. Limited to one bench sign and one trash receptacle sign per lot.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740D64" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(10)</span>
            <span class="li">Signage on coin-operated beverage dispensers, limited to three per lot and not located within the required front yard setback for the zoning district.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740D7D" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(11)</span>
            <span class="li">Graduation banners placed on residentially zoned property. Such banners may be no more than 24 square feet in size and must be maintained in good condition and individually attached to a pole, mast, arm, or other structure. A graduation banner may not be displayed on any lot for more than 60 consecutive days.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740D97" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01; Res. No. SOA2003-001, 5-27-03; Ord. of 9-20-05(6); Res. No. SOA2008-001, 3-25-08; Amd. of 12-16-08, § 3)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE740DB4"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE740DC2">Sec. 86-112.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE740DCD" data-type="subtitle">Maintenance and Appearance of Signs.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE740DE8" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">All signs shall be maintained in good condition, so as to present a neat and orderly appearance. Neglected or dilapidated signs shall be manifested by the following: rust or holes on or in the sign or sign structure, or broken, missing, loose or bent parts, faded or flaking paint, nonoperative or partially nonoperative illuminating or mechanical devices or missing letters in sign copy. The director may cause to be removed after due notice any sign which shows gross neglect or becomes dilapidated.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740E03" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">The department shall give the owner ten days written notice to correct the deficiencies or to remove the sign or signs. If the owner refuses to correct the deficiencies or remove the sign, the department may have the sign removed at the expense of the owner.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9B03" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE740E38"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="xD61FB0B9B07">Sec. 86-113.</h2>
	           <p id="x224282AD12" data-type="subtitle">Illumination of Signs.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE740E66" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">No sign shall give off light which glares, blinds or has any other such adverse effect on traffic or adjacent properties. The light from an illuminated sign shall be established in such a way that adjacent properties and roadways are not adversely affected and that no direct light is cast upon adjacent properties and roadways. No illuminated sign shall be constructed or maintained within 75 feet of the property line of any single-family residential lot.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740E80" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">No sign shall have blinking, flashing, or fluctuating lights or other illuminating devices which have a changing light intensity, brightness or color.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740E98" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">Colored lights shall not be used at any location or in any manner so as to be confused with or construed as traffic control devices. Neither direct nor reflected light from primary light sources shall create a hazard to operators of motor vehicles.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740EBA" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(d)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs located within any residential district may only be indirectly illuminated.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9B15" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE740EEC"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE740EF9">Sec. 86-114.</h2>
	           <p id="xD61FB0B9B1A" data-type="subtitle">Maximum Heights, Maximum Sizes, Setback Requirements and Number Allowance of Signs Permitted.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE740F1C" class="p1">Signs in unincorporated Gwinnett County shall be permitted and regulated in accordance with the following sign table, unless otherwise regulated, prohibited or exempted herein:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE740F2D" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01; Res. No. SOA2003-001, 5-27-03)
<?xpp mccps;std_r270?></p>

      </section>

      <section id="xD61FB0B9B21"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE740F57">Sec. 86-114a.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE740F62" data-type="subtitle">Sign Table.</p>
         </header>

         <table id="x85D3CE740F81" class="std-2">
            <caption/>
            <colgroup data-cols="7">
	              <col width="5.56%"/>
	              <col width="22.22%"/>
	              <col width="33.33%"/>
	              <col width="5.56%"/>
	              <col width="5.56%"/>
	              <col width="22.22%"/>
	              <col width="5.55%"/>
            </colgroup>

            <thead>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>Type of Sign<?quad qa?><br/>Purpose or Use<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
	                 <td>Maximum Height</td>
	                 <td>Setback from Right-of-Way (1)</td>
	                 <td colspan="3">Maximum Size Per Sign Allowed</td>
	                 <td>Number and<?quad qc?><br/>
                     <?quad qa?><br/>Type Permitted<?quad qc?><br/>
                  </td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
               <tr>
	                 <td rowspan="12">1. Primary signs for an individual establishment on an individual nonresidential lot.</td>
	                 <td rowspan="12">5 ft.<?quad qa?><br/>10 ft.<?quad qa?><br/>20 ft.</td>
	                 <td rowspan="12">0—5 ft.<?quad qa?><br/>&gt; 5 ft. or &lt; 20 ft.<?quad qa?><br/>20 ft. or &gt;</td>
	                 <td colspan="3">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
	                 <td rowspan="12">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>One sign structure per road frontage not to exceed maximum allowable square footage.*<?quad qa?><br/>WALL SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>Signs may not exceed 50 percent of the total permitted square footage on any building elevation. The total of all signs on all elevations shall not exceed the total square footage lists.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Gross Building Space</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Max. Sign Size</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>0—10,000</td>
	                 <td>75 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>10,001—50,000</td>
	                 <td>100 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>50,001—100,000</td>
	                 <td>150 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>100,000— &gt;</td>
	                 <td>200 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="3">WALL SIGNS:<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Gross Building Space</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Max Sign Size</u>
                     <?quad qc?><br/>
                     <?quad qa?><br/>
                     <u>Per Elevation</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Agg. Total<?quad qa?><br/>all Elev.</u>
                  </td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>0—2,500</td>
	                 <td>36 s.f.</td>
	                 <td>72 s.f.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>2,501—15,000</td>
	                 <td>60 s.f.</td>
	                 <td>120 s.f.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>15,001—50,000</td>
	                 <td>100 s.f.</td>
	                 <td>200 s.f.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>50,001— &gt;</td>
	                 <td>200 s.f.</td>
	                 <td>400 s.f.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td rowspan="6">2. Accessory ground signs for an individual establishment on an individual nonresidential lot.</td>
	                 <td rowspan="6">3 ft.</td>
	                 <td rowspan="6">0—5 ft.</td>
	                 <td colspan="3">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
	                 <td rowspan="2">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>Two sign structures per entrance.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Gross Building Space</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Max. Sign Size</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>0—10,000</td>
	                 <td>3 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>10,001—50,000</td>
	                 <td>4 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>50,001—100,000</td>
	                 <td>5 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>100,000— &gt;</td>
	                 <td>6 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td rowspan="8">3. Primary signs for an individual building on an individual residential lot.</td>
	                 <td>5 ft.</td>
	                 <td>0 ft.</td>
	                 <td colspan="3">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
	                 <td rowspan="8">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>One sign structure per road frontage not to exceed maximum allowable square footage.<?quad qa?><br/>WALL SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>Signs may not exceed one placed on the front elevation.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Lot acreage</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Max. Sign Size</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>3—5 acres</td>
	                 <td>24 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>5 or greater</td>
	                 <td>48 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td colspan="2">WALL SIGNS:<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Lot acreage</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Max. Sign Size</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>3—5 acres</td>
	                 <td>9 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>5 or greater</td>
	                 <td>18 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td rowspan="4">4. Accessory ground signs for an individual building on an individual residential lot.</td>
	                 <td>3 ft.</td>
	                 <td>0 ft.</td>
	                 <td colspan="3">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
	                 <td rowspan="2">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>Two sign structures per entrance.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Lot acreage</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Max. Sign Size</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>3—5 acres</td>
	                 <td>4 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>5 or greater</td>
	                 <td>6 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td rowspan="11">5. Signs for individual establishments, shops, etc. within a planned commercial center.</td>
	                 <td rowspan="11">Not greater than height of wall</td>
	                 <td rowspan="11">N/A</td>
	                 <td colspan="3">WALL SIGNS:<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
	                 <td rowspan="11">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>Not allowed.<?quad qa?><br/>WALL SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>Signs may not exceed 50 percent of the total permitted square footage on any building elevation. The total of all wall signs on all elevations shall not exceed the total square footage listed.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Gross Building Space</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Max Sign Size Per Bldg. Elevation</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>0—2,500</td>
	                 <td>36 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>2,501—15,000</td>
	                 <td>60 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>15,001—50,000</td>
	                 <td>100 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>50,000— &gt;</td>
	                 <td>200 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Gross Building Space</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Aggregate Total of All Wall Signs</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>0—2,500</td>
	                 <td>72 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>2,501—15,000</td>
	                 <td>120 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>15,001—50,000</td>
	                 <td>200 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>50,001— &gt;</td>
	                 <td>400 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>6. Signs for individual offices, etc. within a planned office or industrial center.</td>
	                 <td>Not greater than height of wall</td>
	                 <td>N/A</td>
	                 <td colspan="3">20 square feet or five percent of the wall areas, whichever is greater<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
	                 <td>GROUND SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>Not allowed<?quad qa?><br/>WALL SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>One per building elevation per tenant</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td rowspan="6">7. Primary ground sign for planned office, commercial, industrial or retail center.</td>
	                 <td rowspan="6">5 ft.<?quad qa?><br/>10 ft.<?quad qa?><br/>20 ft.</td>
	                 <td rowspan="6">0—5 ft.<?quad qa?><br/>&gt; 5 or &lt; 20 ft.<?quad qa?><br/>20 ft. or &gt;</td>
	                 <td colspan="3">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
	                 <td rowspan="6">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>One sign structure per road frontage not to exceed maximum allowable square footage.*</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Gross Building Space</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Max. Sign Size</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>0—10,000</td>
	                 <td>75 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>10,001—50,000</td>
	                 <td>100 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>50,001—100,000</td>
	                 <td>150 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>100,000— &gt;</td>
	                 <td>200 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td rowspan="5">8. Accessory ground sign for planned office, commercial, industrial or retail center.</td>
	                 <td>3 ft.</td>
	                 <td>0—5 ft.</td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Gross Building Space</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td>
                     <u>Max. Sign Size</u>
                  </td>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td rowspan="5">GROUND SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>Two sign structures per entrance.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>0—10,000</td>
	                 <td>3 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>10,001—50,000</td>
	                 <td>4 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>50,001—100,000</td>
	                 <td>5 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>100,000— &gt;</td>
	                 <td>6 s.f.</td>
	                 <td/>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>9. Permanent entrance sign for a nonresidential subdivision.</td>
	                 <td><?conv chgcell;jstyle;rr?>8 ft. excluding embellishments which shall not exceed two feet above the maximum height of the sign structure.</td>
	                 <td>0 ft.</td>
	                 <td>50 square feet</td>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>Two per entrance</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>10. Permanent entrance sign for a residential development or subdivision.</td>
	                 <td><?conv chgcell;jstyle;rr?>8 ft. excluding embellishments which shall not exceed two feet above the maximum height of the sign structure.</td>
	                 <td>0 ft.</td>
	                 <td colspan="3">32 square feet per sign (sign structure must be constructed of brick, stone, masonry or equal architectural material).<?quad ql?><br/>
                  </td>
	                 <td>Two per entrance</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>11. Interior Project Directional Sign (See section 86-118)</td>
	                 <td>4 ft.</td>
	                 <td>0 ft.</td>
	                 <td>32 square feet</td>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>One per internal intersection</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>12. Permanent sign for a subdivision recreation area.</td>
	                 <td>5 Ft.</td>
	                 <td>0 Ft.</td>
	                 <td colspan="3">GROUND SIGNS—24 square feet<?quad qa?><br/>WALL SIGNS—9 square feet</td>
	                 <td>GROUND SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>One sign structure per road frontage not to exceed the maximum allowable square footage.<?quad qa?><br/>WALL SIGNS:<?quad qa?><br/>Signs shall not exceed one placed on the front elevation.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td colspan="7"> _____</td>
               </tr>
            </tbody>
         </table>

         <p id="x85D3CE741773" class="b1"><?conv sz;8q?>(1) No sign shall be located closer than ten feet to the back of curb of a public roadway.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7417A3" class="b1"><?conv sz;8q?>* Properties with multiple road frontages may transfer a maximum of 50 percent of the allowable square footage from one road frontage to the other.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7417B6" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01; Res. No. SOA2003-001, 5-27-03)

<?xpp mccps;standard?>
</p>

      </section>

      <section id="xD61FB0B9BFD"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE7417F8">Sec. 86-115.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE741804" data-type="subtitle">Oversized Signs.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE74181C" class="p1">Oversized signs shall be permitted subject to the following restrictions:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74182E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Oversized signs may be permitted as an allowed use within the C-2, C-3, and M-2 districts, or by special use permit within the M-1 district, if located on properties that are adjacent to principal arterials, major arterials or state or national highways. Oversized signs shall be prohibited along parkways or roads designated as residential arterials as shown in the county comprehensive plan.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74184C" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Oversized signs shall not be placed within 500 feet of a dwelling, residential zoning district, county building, church, school, daycare, park cemetery, or right-of-way of a parkway.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741865" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Oversized signs shall not be less than 1,250 feet from the limits of any overlay zoning district where they are prohibited or from any other oversized sign in any direction, on either side of the same right-of-way or along another right-of-way.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74187E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Oversized signs shall be completely independent of any building or other structure, excluding the sign structure.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741895" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Oversized signs shall meet the area, public street frontage, side yard, and rear yard requirements of the zoning district in which located.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7418B1" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">The maximum sign area of all display surfaces shall not exceed 700 square feet per sign structure. For double-faced signs, these maximum sign areas shall apply to each side of the sign structure.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7418C9" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">No oversized sign shall contain more than two faces per side, nor more than two sides; provided, however, that no sign face may be located above another sign face.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9C17" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">The maximum height and minimum front yard setback from the street right-of-way for oversized signs are:</span>
         </p>

         <table id="x85D3CE741916" class="b1 std-2">
            <caption/>
            <colgroup data-cols="3">
	              <col width="33.33%"/>
	              <col width="33.33%"/>
	              <col width="33.34%"/>
            </colgroup>

            <thead/>

            <tbody>

               <tr>
	                 <td>Sign Face in One Direction</td>
	                 <td>Maximum Height</td>
	                 <td>Minimum Front Yard Setback</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>350 sq. ft. or greater</td>
	                 <td>70 ft. if adjacent to I-85 or I-985</td>
	                 <td>75 ft.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td/>
	                 <td>40 ft. (all other roads)</td>
	                 <td>75 ft.</td>
               </tr>
               <tr>
	                 <td>300-349 sq. ft.</td>
	                 <td>30 ft.</td>
	                 <td>50 ft.</td>
               </tr>
            </tbody>
         </table>

         <p id="x85D3CE7419B6" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(9)</span>
            <span class="li">An increase in maximum height of an oversized sign may be permitted provided the applicant for such an increase is granted a special use permit by the board of commissioners after receiving recommendations from the planning director and planning commission and after a public hearing, subject to the following conditions:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7419E1" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">a.</span>
            <span class="li">The increase in maximum height shall not exceed 25 percent of the allowable maximum height specified in the table above.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9C33" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">b.</span>
            <span class="li">The oversized sign shall be a conforming sign.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741A17" class="ol3">
            <span class="incr">c.</span>
            <span class="li">The oversized sign has been blocked from view by subsequent development.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741A33" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(10)</span>
            <span class="li">No more than three oversized signs shall be permitted per quadrant of any interchange adjacent to I-85 and I-985 north of the S.R. 316 and I-85 interchange. These signs are restricted to an area 1,200 feet long beginning 500 feet from the point where the pavement widens on the main traveled way to accommodate the longest entrance or exit ramps.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741A53" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(11)</span>
            <span class="li">No oversized sign shall be placed within the Mall of Georgia Overlay District.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741A6B" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01; Res. No. SOA2003-001, 5-27-03)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE741A8C"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE741A9A">Sec. 86-116.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE741AA5" data-type="subtitle">Subdivision Directional Signs.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE741ABE" class="p1">Subdivision directional signs shall be permitted within any zoning district, provided they serve a temporary purpose, are maintained in an attractive and sound manner, and are removed at the owner's expense. They are intended to encourage parties involved in subdivision development projects in proximity to one another to work together and place directional information for multiple projects on one sign or sign structure. Subdivision directional signs may be allowed for a period of time from the beginning of the project until ten days following the sale of the final property. Subdivision directional signs shall be subject to the following requirements:</p>

         <p id="x156991AC2D4" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Shall not be located within ten feet of the pavement of any street and shall not be permitted on any public right-of-way.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741AF3" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Shall not be illuminated or affixed in any manner to trees, street or light poles, utility poles, other signs or sign structures.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741B0F" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Shall be made of wood.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741B28" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Shall include the name, address and phone number of the owner or party responsible for the removal and maintenance of the sign. This information must be written in weatherproof ink or paint on at least one face of the sign in letters not exceeding one-half inch in height.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741B41" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Shall be located no greater than two miles or two intersections as shown on the long range road classification map, whichever is greater, from the project or property to which they refer, as measured along existing streets.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741B5A" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Signs prohibited under this article shall not be used as a subdivision directional sign.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741B72" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">Subdivision directional signs shall not exceed 24 square feet in total sign area per face with no one project allowed more than four total square feet per face (four projects per face) and shall not exceed eight feet in height excluding embellishments which shall not exceed two feet above the maximum height of the sign structure.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741BCD" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(8)</span>
            <span class="li">Subdivision directional signs shall be limited to four per intersection with no more than one per corner.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741BE6" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(9)</span>
            <span class="li">Subdivision directional signs shall be located within 200 feet of an intersection but no closer than 20 feet from the intersection.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741BFE" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(10)</span>
            <span class="li">These signs require a sign permit.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741C19" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE741C33"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE741C41">Sec. 86-117.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE741C4B" data-type="subtitle">Convenience Stores and Service Stations With Pump Islands.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE741C62" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">Convenience stores and service stations with pump islands may have additional signage subject to the following limitations:</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741C7D" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Two signs per canopy face with a maximum of 8 square feet per sign.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741C95" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Spreader bars (signs located under canopy over pumps islands) shall be limited to no more than two signs per spreader bar, not to exceed four square feet per sign. However, total square footage for all spreader bars shall not exceed 24 square feet.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741CAD" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Accessory car wash, if a separate drive-through car wash building is on site, two additional wall signs may be allowed not to exceed eight square feet each.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741CC5" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE741CE1"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE741CF0">Sec. 86-118.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE741CFB" data-type="subtitle">Interior Project Directional Sign.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE741D12" class="p1">Such signs are authorized in all developments or planned subdivisions of land within any nonresidential zoning district subject to the following:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741D23" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">May not be located within 100 feet of an entrance to a project.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9C86" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Maximum sign area shall not exceed 32 square feet.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741D55" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Maximum sign height shall not exceed four feet.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741D6D" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">Setback from right-of-way may be zero feet.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741D84" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">Only one such sign may be located at each internal intersection of private driveways or public streets within the project.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741D9E" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">The purpose of the sign is to provide more definitive directional information concerning the whereabouts of tenants within the development.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741DBA" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE741DD4"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE741DE2">Sec. 86-119.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE741DEC" data-type="subtitle">Permit Approval, Denial or Revocation.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE741E06" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(a)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Procedure.</i> An action by the department to approve or deny a sign permit shall be taken within 30 days of receipt of a complete sign permit application. Any sign permit application for which no action has been taken after 30 days or more shall be deemed to be approved.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741E23" class="p1">The director shall deny permit application(s) for signs that do not comply with the provisions of this article, incomplete applications, and applications containing any false material statements. A violation of any provision of this article and any other applicable state laws or county ordinances will be grounds for terminating a permit granted by the county for the erection of a sign. Should it be determined that a sign permit was issued pursuant to an incomplete application or an application containing a false material statement, or that a permit has been erroneously issued in violation of this article, the director shall revoke the permit. Should the director deny a permit, the reasons for the denial are to be stated in writing and mailed by certified mail, return receipt requested, to the address on the permit application, postmarked on or before the 30th business day after the director's receipt of the application, or by hand delivery to the applicant at time of denial. Any application denied and later resubmitted shall be deemed to have been submitted on the date of resubmission, not the date of the original submission. A permit shall not be denied or revoked except for due cause, being the violation of the provisions of this article, other applicable ordinances, state or federal law, or the submission of an incomplete application or an application containing false material statements.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741E37" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(b)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Appeal.</i> A person whose permit application has been denied or a permittee whose permit has been revoked may appeal the decision of the director to the zoning board of appeals as provided.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741E4F" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(c)</span>
            <span class="li">
               <i>Certiorari.</i> In the event a person whose permit has been denied or revoked is dissatisfied with the decision of the zoning board of appeals, they may petition for writ of certiorari to the superior court of the county as provided by law.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741E6A" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE741E85"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE741E93">Sec. 86-120.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE741E9D" data-type="subtitle">Variances.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE741EB6" class="p1">Where a literal application of this article, due to special circumstances, would result in an unusual hardship in an individual case, a variance may be granted by the zoning board of appeals pursuant to procedures set forth including, but not limited to:</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741ECF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">Exceptional conditions pertaining to the property where the sign is to be located as a result of its size, shape, or topography, which are not applicable to other lands or structures in the area.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741EE7" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">The applicant would be deprived of rights that are commonly enjoyed by others similarly situated.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741EFF" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Granting the variance would not confer on the applicant any significant privileges which are denied to others similarly situated.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741F19" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">The exceptional circumstances are not the result of action by the applicant.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="xD61FB0B9CB8" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(5)</span>
            <span class="li">The requested variance is the minimum variance necessary to allow the applicant to enjoy the rights commonly enjoyed by others similarly situated.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741F82" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(6)</span>
            <span class="li">Granting of the variance would not violate more than one standard of this article.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741F9B" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(7)</span>
            <span class="li">Granting the variance would not result in allowing a sign that interferes with road or highway visibility or obstruct or otherwise interfere with the safe and orderly movement of traffic.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE741FB3" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE741FCD"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE741FDD">Sec. 86-121.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE741FE8" data-type="subtitle">Enforcement and Penalties.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE741FFF" class="p1">The sign provisions of this article shall be administered and enforced by the director.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE742010" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">The director or designee may issue a citation for violation of this article by any person, including, if applicable, the owner, manager or tenant of the lot on which a sign is located; for a sign erected, altered, maintained, converted, or used in violation of this article; or in violation of any other applicable ordinance, including, but not limited to, building or electrical codes.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE742029" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">Any person violating any provision of this article shall be guilty of an offense, and upon conviction by a court of competent jurisdiction, shall be subject to a penalty of not less than $25.00 nor more than $1,000.00, or by confinement in the county jail for a total time not to exceed 60 days, or both, and may not be stayed or suspended.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE742044" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">The county may seek affirmative equitable relief in a court of competent jurisdiction to cause the removal or repair of any sign in violation of this or other county ordinances.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74205D" class="ol2">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">The director or his/her designee may remove any sign or structure illegally placed upon a public right-of-way without any notice and may dispose of said sign or structure by taking it to any landfill. Such removal and disposal of illegally placed signs shall not preclude the prosecution of any person for illegally placing such signs in the public right-of-way.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE742077" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE742091"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE7420A1">Sec. 86-122.</h2>
	           <p id="x156991AC2E3" data-type="subtitle">Zoning Ordinance.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE7420C4" class="p1">Except as provided elsewhere in this article, to the extent that it is not inconsistent with this article, the county zoning resolution, as amended including, but not limited to definitions of terms contained therein, is incorporated as a part of this article as if fully restated herein for the same purposes stated in section 86-100 hereof and for the same purposes for which the zoning resolution and any amendments thereto, were adopted, which purposes are expressly incorporated herein. However, to the extent that any regulations governing any zoning district now existing or later enacted conflict with this article, the rules of the zoning district shall control.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE7420D7" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE7420F7"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE742107">Sec. 86-123.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE742111" data-type="subtitle">Severability.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE74212D" class="p1">In the event any section, subsection, sentence, or word of this article is declared and adjudged to be invalidated or unconstitutional, such declaration or adjudication shall not affect the remaining portions of this chapter, which shall remain in full force and effect as if such portion so declared or adjudged unconstitutional were not originally part of this chapter, even if the surviving parts of the ordinance result in greater restrictions after any unconstitutional provisions are stricken. The board of commissioners declares that it would have enacted the remaining parts of this chapter if it had known that such portion thereof would be declared or adjudged invalid or unconstitutional. The board of commissioners declares its intent that should this article be declared invalid in part or in whole, signs are to be subject to regulations applicable to structures contained in other ordinances, including the zoning resolution.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE742143" class="historynote1">(Res. No. A-01-004, 8-28-01)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE74215D"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE74216B">Sec. 86-124.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE742176" data-type="subtitle">Customary Home Occupation Signs Prohibited.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE74218D" class="p1">For each parcel of real property upon which a customary home occupation is conducted, as defined in Section 607 of the 1985 Zoning Resolution of Gwinnett County, a sign advertising the customary home occupation conducted on the premises shall be prohibited. There shall be no exterior evidence of the conduct of the home occupation upon such premises.</p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74219F" class="historynote1">(Amd. of 12-16-08, § 4)</p>

      </section>

      <section id="x85D3CE7421B9"
               class="section"
               data-type="sect2"
               data-pubmap="section">
         <header>
	           <h2 id="x85D3CE7421C7">Sec. 86-125.</h2>
	           <p id="x85D3CE7421D1" data-type="subtitle">Annual Registration of Oversized Signs.</p>
         </header>

         <p id="x85D3CE7421E8" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(1)</span>
            <span class="li">On or before May 1 of each calendar year, the owner of any oversized sign shall register such sign with the Director of the Gwinnett County Department of Planning and Development on a form (or via electronic means) substantially similar to that attached hereto [Ordinance No. SO-2011-1] as Exhibit "A". The initial annual registration shall identify such oversized sign by tax parcel number, physical street address, or GIS coordinates, and shall describe all structures and equipment on the site associated with such oversized signs. Annually thereafter, each subsequent registration shall identify any transfer of ownership of such sign, and/or any modifications to such sign which occurred during the preceding calendar year.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE742203" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(2)</span>
            <span class="li">For all oversized signs which were constructed more than ten years prior to the submittal of the annual registration, at least once every three years the owner of such sign shall submit certification to the director that such sign was inspected by an employee or authorized agent of the owner whose responsibilities and job duties include the inspection and maintenance of signs for such sign owner that no signs of defect, disrepair, or other hazardous condition exist.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE74221C" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(3)</span>
            <span class="li">Any sign owner which owns more than 20 oversized signs subject to subsection (2) shall be deemed to be in compliance with its requirements so long as all of such sign owner's oversized signs which are more than ten years old are inspected within three years of the first deadline for registration under this section.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE742235" class="ol1">
            <span class="incr">(4)</span>
            <span class="li">The annual registration fee for each oversized sign shall be $100.00 per sign per year for the first registration and $50.00 per sign per year for each subsequent year.</span>
         </p>

         <p id="x85D3CE742297" class="historynote1">(Ord. of 6-15-10, § 2; Ord. of 12-14-10, § 2; Ord. of 6-28-11, § 1; Ord. No. TOO2011-2, Attach. 1, 9-27-11; Ord. No. SO-2011-1, Attach. 1, 10-25-11)
</p>

      </section>
   </section>
</section>
